music
music
applause
applause
Today's Feast of Knowledge
今天的這個知識饗宴
So first I would like to introduce today's keynote speaker
那麼首先我要介紹今天的主講者
Today's speaker is Academician Zhang Zhenghua
今天主講者是張正華院士
So
那麼
I think everyone should be familiar with his name.
我想大家對他的名字應該都不陌生
Well, Academician Zhang is a world-renowned archaeologist
那麼張院士呢是世界知名的考古學者
He is the Department of Archaeological Anthropology of National Taiwan University
他是台大考古人類學系
Graduated from the School of Archeology and Anthropology, National Taiwan University
跟台大考古人類學院就所畢業
yes then graduating from harvard
是然後哈佛大學畢業
So he has actually been from
那麼他目前事實上也一直從
from his first job
從他第一個工作開始
at the Institute of Historical Linguistics at Academia Sinica
就在中央研究院的歷史語言研究所
then now as a Distinguished Research Fellow
那麼現在擔任特聘研究員
His research information is mainly Taiwan
他的研究信息主要是台灣
Realization culture in South China and Southeast Asia
華南跟東南亞等地區的實現文化
over the past 40 years
在過去40多年中
He has led more than a dozen large-scale projects
他領導過十多項大型的計畫
large archaeological project
大型的考古計畫
Including the excavation of the very famous Shisanhang ruins
包括非常有名的十三行遺址的發掘
Archaeological Survey of the Grand Ducey Valley
大杜西河谷考古調查
Archaeological research on the history of ancient human extension
古代人類拓之史的考古學研究
Archaeological Research on the North Shore of the Philippines
菲律賓屋屋屋屋北岸的考古學研究
But the most interesting thing to draw attention to is the
但是最有意引起大家注意的是
started more than ten years ago
十多年前開始的
Nanke Ancient Culture This
南科古代文化的這個
Rescue plan for ruins
遺址的搶救計畫
Nananke Ancient Cultural Relics Rescue Project Institute
那南科古代文化遺址搶救計畫所
Many cultural relics unearthed
出土的文物之多
this
這個
The importance of academic significance
學術意義之重要
i think it's hard to have
我想很難有
comparable to this
可以相比倫比的這個
in 2009
在2009年
Mr. Zhang has given many tasks to Taitung County at the Ministry of Culture
張先生授文化部級台東縣任務之多
Entrusted the implementation of Taitung Changbing's
委託執行了台東長兵的
Baxiandong National Site Survey Project
八仙洞國地遺址調查計畫
that's because of this
那因為這個
What I'm doing at this time is the director
這個時候我正在做的所長
Year 2009
2009年
I am the late director
我這是所長的後期
so i know all of this
所以這些我都很清楚
I have also visited the ruins of Nanke
南科的遺址我也去看過
I also offered
我也去供過
Unearthed skeletons of many people across the ages
出土的很多跨時代的人的骨骸
I forgot whether it was Zhang Xian or who told me
我忘了是張憲還是誰跟我說
Someday these cars will be brought back to the research institute
哪一天要把這些車回來研究院
I was shocked
我聽了嚇一跳
Because there is no place in the research institute to put so many
因為研究院哪有地方可以放這麼多的
Maybe I don't know if it's Zhang Xian or who was the staff at that time
或許我也不知道是張憲還是誰當時的工作人員
when joking
開玩笑的時候
because a lot
因為非常多
very large
數目非常之大
So Baxiandong Chair
所以八仙洞椅子
After four years of intensive and systematic investigation
經過四年密集而系統的調查
Determined the chronology and cultural connotation of Taiwan's old culture
確定了台灣舊時期文化的年代學跟文化內涵
Push back the history of human beings living in Taiwan to 30,000 years ago
把人類死居台灣的歷史上推到三萬年前
So this is a very important project
所以這是一個也非常有重要意義的計畫
besides
除此之外
Academician Zhang is also keen on applying archaeology to social services
張院士也熱衷於考古學運用於社會服務
i think you remember
我想各位記得
Last time this TransAsia Airways
上次這個復興航空
Unfortunately, this plane is the best
這飛機不幸這個最機
In the end, there was no way Mr. Zhang led the archaeological team
最後沒辦法張先生率下考古隊
with the most sophisticated detectors
用最精密的探測儀
At that time, the TV interviewed Mr. Zhang
那時候電視有訪問張先生
I have seen
我有看到
I think you may have seen
我想各位或許有看到過
He often assists the government in carrying out the work of preserving cultural assets
他經常協助政府執行文化資產保存的工作
And from 2002 to 2006
而且從2002到2006年
Curator of the National Taiwan Shijie Culture Museum
擔任國立台灣史杰文化博物館的館長
There are many contributions to this Shijie cultural museum
對這個史杰文化博物館的貢獻很多
He also leads the commission of the socio-cultural museum
他同時也領導社會文化博的委託
Leading the Academia Sinica underwater archeology team
領導中央研究院水下考古團隊
There has also now been quite a bit of investigation
現在也進行了相當多的調查
grades
成績匪然
Please don't underestimate underwater archeology
請各位不要小看水下考古
Because at this time I am also the director
因為這個時候我也在當所長
So to train in underwater archaeology
所以要訓練水下考古
I want to dive to Ximan in a fast class seaside place in Taoyuan
要潛到洗漫在桃園的一個快階級海邊的地方
The film is very capable of continuing when you and I go to support
片記非常能夠開續點你我去支持的時候
I still remember
我還記得
that was very hard work
那是非常辛苦的工作
The trainee program
那個學員訓練的項目
so this works
所以這個工作
and it's groundbreaking
而且是開創性的
Taiwan did not have such a
台灣之前並沒有這樣的一個
Formal Archaeological Team
正式的考古團隊
underwater archeology team
水下考古團隊
He also currently serves as
他目前還擔任
Chairman of the Chinese Association of Underwater Archaeology
中華水下考古協會理事長
promote civil participation
推動民間參與
Protection and promotion of underwater cultural assets
水下文化資產的保護跟宣導
That Mr. Zhang has a lot of trials
那張先生的試積非常多
There are many wind industry crises
風工危機非常多
There is no way to introduce Yiyi here
在這裡沒辦法依依介紹
The topic he is going to talk about today is
他今天要講的題目是
Stories of Ancient Taiwanese
古代台灣人的故事
we welcome him with warm applause
我們以熱烈的掌聲歡迎他
thank you very much
非常謝謝
Vice President Wang
王副院長
Vice President Wang just gave me an introduction
王副院長剛給我的介紹
actually
其實
Vice President Wang is my old officer
王副院長是我老長官
In the past, he was our director when he was in the eleventh institute
過去在十一所的時候就是我們的所長
now our vice president
現在是我們的副院長
So a lot of things he just said
所以很多事情剛剛他講過了
under his leadership
都是在他的領導之下
can be executed smoothly
可以順利的來執行
then i personally
那麼我個人
In fact, time is very fast in this field
其实在这个领域时间很快
It's been 40 years all of a sudden
一下子悠悠了40年了
this time is very long
这个时间非常久
Actually in all my work
其实在我的所有工作里面
The last thing that came together was this
最后拼凑出来的就是这个
Stories of Ancient Taiwanese
古代台湾人的故事
because of my expertise
因为我的专长
Although I also work in surrounding areas of Taiwan
我虽然也做台湾周边地区的
Archeology of Mainland Southeast Asia
大陆的东南亚的考古
But after all, Taiwan is still me
但是毕竟台湾还是我一个
main field of work
主要的一个工作的场域
So in the past 30-40 years
所以在过去30-40年里面
Actually the work I do
其实我所做的工作
The ultimate purpose is to go
最后的目的就是要去
The stories of ancient people in Taiwan
把台湾古代人的故事
able to piece together
能够拼凑起来
So I bring up this topic today
所以我今天提出这个题目
I think the story of the ancient Taiwanese
我想古代台湾人的故事
let me talk for an hour and a half
我就一个半小时让我讲
Actually, I think that what you say
其实我觉得这样讲的话
It should be like a thousand and one nights
应该是如一千零一夜
just tell a story
就是说一个故事一个讲的话
Really can add a lot of stories
真的可以加非常多的故事
But today I can only be very general
但是我今天也只能够很笼统的
very simply
很简单的来说
Let's talk about the story of this ancient Taiwanese
来谈一谈这个古代台湾人的故事
Of course, this story is not One Thousand and One Nights.
那这故事当然不是一千零一夜了
just one night it won't arrive
就一夜它不到
Then I say today is easy
那么我说今天很简单
if anything is unclear
如果有任何不清楚的地方的话
Also please give me advice
还请大家给我指教
So
那么
My computer here is not very
这边我这个电脑还不太
OK
OK
This is another page
这个换一页
Originally, this mouse should be able to change a page
本来这个这个滑鼠应该可以换一页的
I don't know why it can't be changed
我不曉得为什么不能换
this can be replaced
这个可以换一
this is ok
这个OK
sorry for this
很抱歉这个
no page change
没换一页
here
在这里啊
ok good
OK好
then i want this
那么我想这个
Before today's story, I will make a beginning
我今天这个故事之前先做一个开头
then i want to be in taiwan
那么我想在台湾
One of the most familiar questions is that Taiwanese people
大家最熟悉的一个问题就是随时台湾人
I think everyone in the media is on the news
我想大家在媒体在新闻上面
Go online and check Google
上網去查一查 Google 一下
This very, very much these discussions
這個非常非常多的這些的議論
these discussions these coups
這些討論 這些政變
So this Taiwan as a look at all kinds of
所以這台灣作為看各種各樣的
the same view
這種一樣的看法
Well in fact there are many
那麼事實上有很多
It stems from a different view of history
它是源於不同的史觀
We can't say who is right and who is wrong
我們不能講誰對 誰錯
but basically
但基本上面
This is due to many different historical views
這個就是源於很多不同的史觀
Well, I'll just list a few now.
那麼我現在隨便列幾個出來
Then the first and most famous is
那麼第一個最有名的就是
Lianheng's Taiwan General Studies
聯橫的台灣通識
Then this as a view of history
那麼這個作為看它的史觀
It is basically the historical view of the consciousness of the Han nationality
基本上是漢族意識的史觀
So from its Taiwan general knowledge sequence
所以從它的這個台灣通識序裡面
It says Taiwan is not true
它說台灣故不實也
Who started it is exactly what made it
何人起之 正是作之
Yingzhi in the Qing Dynasty Enlightenment also has a temper
清代營之 開悟成物也有脾氣
As for more than three hundred years ago
至於今三百餘年予
then this obviously
那這個顯然
It is a Chinese perspective
它是一個以漢人作為觀點的
such a view of history
這樣的一個史觀
that this
那這個
Then another very famous
那麼另外一個非常有名的
it's totally different
這是完全是不一樣
in the opposite direction
一反方向的
This is the famous historical name
這是有名的這個史名
It says to write the four hundred years history of Taiwanese
它說寫著台灣人四百年史
you see it in front of it
你看它在它的前面
He also said that general laws concerning the development of human society
他也說把有關人類社會發展一般法則
the universal truth of social development
即使社會發展的普遍真理
Combined with these historical realities of Taiwan
和這些台灣的歷史現實結合起來
Then try to grasp the reality of Taiwan
然後竭力把握台灣的實相
Re-establish Taiwan's view of history
再確立了台灣的史觀
So one of his views on history
所以他的一個史觀呢
Basically based on the development of Taiwan's national theory
基本上是以台灣民族論的作出發展
a view of history developed
所發展出來的一個歷史觀
What about another historian?
那麼另外一位史觀呢
This is the vice president of our college in the past
這個是過去我們院的副院長
Where is Vice President Zhang Guangzhe?
張光哲副院長呢
Then one of his views on history
那麼他的一個史觀
so what did he say
那麼他說呢
He is due to Taiwan's island environment
他是由於台灣的島嶼環境
Complexity of geography and terrain
地理位置和地形的複雜性
What about our research on Taiwan history?
我們在台灣史的研究上面呢
And we must adopt a more obvious perspective of cultural ecology
又必須採取比較顯明的文化生態學的觀點
And because the 2 billion indigenous peoples on Taiwan Island
又由於台灣島上20億萬土著民族
Therefore, the history of Taiwan contains a very important history of indigenous peoples
所以台灣史裡面包含著非常重要的土著民族史
The New Components of the Relationship with the Han Dynasty
與漢藩關係的新成分
So he learned from the cultural ecology of an entire island
所以他是從一個整個島嶼上面的文化生態學的
such a point of view
這樣一個觀點
the relationship between the person
這個人和人之間的關係
This view of human interaction
人和人之間的互動的這種觀點
to develop
來發展出來
one of his views on history
他的一個史觀
Another recent one
另外最近的這個
Cao Yong and Academician Cao who just passed away
剛剛過世的這個曹永和曹院士
Then what he proposed
那麼他所提出來的
Also known as Taiwan Island History View
也叫台灣島史觀
so he thinks
所以他認為
Our Research on the Island of Taiwan
我們對於台灣島的研究
should get rid of these political
應該擺脫這些政治的
these positions
這些立場
some of these politics
這些政治的一些
Some perspectives on change
變遷的一些觀點
Rather, from the history of the people on the island of Taiwan
而是要從台灣島上的人民的歷史
Just a separate from this island
就從這個島一個獨立的
a stage of history
一個歷史的舞台
to explain the development of our Taiwan
來解釋我們台灣的發展
Therefore, from the perspective of Taiwan island history
所以他從一個台灣島史的觀點
to provide such a
來提供出這樣一個
A Viewpoint on Taiwan's History
台灣史的一個史觀
So because of this different view of history
所以因此這個不同的史觀
tends to develop naturally
往往自然會發展出來
for taiwan
對於台灣
who is taiwanese
誰是台灣人
such an issue
這樣一個議題
there will be something different
會有一些不同的
some opinions
一些看法
this is very much
這個非常多
check as if
作為假如查一查
on the media
在媒體上面
on the page
在網頁上面
various of these
各種各樣這些
Randomly list out a few
隨便列了幾樣出來
result everyone
結果每一個人
He has different viewpoints
都有他不同的這些觀點
leftist
有左派的
There are also various viewpoints
也有各種各樣不同的觀點
So these things have actually become a big kind of entanglement in our Taiwanese society today, or one left over two.
所以這些東西其實變成今天我們台灣社會裡一個很大的一種糾葛或者一剩二一種
disturbance
紛擾
so what about me today
那麼可是我今天呢
I'm a person who studies archaeology. What's the advantage?
我就學考古的人一個好處呢
I can ignore people now
我可以不管現在的人
because people are alive now
因為現在人是活人
right
對不對
to speak face to face
要面對面講話的
to see
要看的
to discuss
要討論的
to argue
要爭辯的
but what about me today
可是我今天呢
I met the ancient people
是和古代的人相遇
So it's simpler
所以就比較單純一些
then i want this
那麼我想這個
After the research of this ancient man
從這個古代人研究之後呢
What can we do with our research
我們可以利用我們的研究呢
go back and think about it
再回頭反思一下
who is taiwanese
到底誰是台灣人
Then their survival and development trajectory in Taiwan
然後他們在台灣的生存和發展的軌跡
but what
而是什麼
What are the traits they can conceive?
他們能夠所孕育出來的特質又是什麼
Then what
然後呢
What about us Taiwanese today?
對於我們今天台灣人呢
What kind of inspiration can he offer
他能夠提供什麼樣的啟示
I think this is what we actually
我想這也是我們其實
Generally speaking, we archaeologists
一般講說我們做考古學的人呢
Is an ivory tower of knowledge
是一個象牙塔的學問
We just locked ourselves in an ivory tower to do research
我們完全就是把自己關在象牙塔裡面去做研究
has nothing to do with today's society
和現在社會沒有關係
I think this is a completely wrong point of view
我想這完全是一個其實不對的觀點
In fact, Vice President Wang also explained just now
其實剛剛王副院長也解釋了
actually
其實
We who do archaeology don't just care about society
我們做考古學的人不只關心社會
And many of them are actually closely related to society.
而且很多其實和社會有很密切的
these interactions
這些互動的關係
Just now, Wangfu mentioned that the recent complex air crash
剛剛王府講提到說最近這個複形空難
We actually have a place where archeology can play our role
我們竟然考古學還可以發揮我們的用武之地
We can also use our expertise
我們這個還可以用我們的專長
To assist in this financial river
去協助到這個金融河裡面
Go hunt for these scumbags of this plane crash
去搜尋這些這個空難的淋濫者
Well, of course there are many other developments in our society
那麼當然另外還有很多我們社會的發展
some cultural issues
一些文化的議題
In fact, archaeologists are very active in participating in
其實考古學者都非常的積極地去參與
So we have a saying
所以我們有一句俗話講
Archaeologists from Taiwan
說台灣的考古學者
His other name is Fire Brigade
他另外一個名稱叫救火隊
Because he went to fight the fire all day and night
因為他一天當晚就去救火
Because there are too many things in Taiwan that need cultural rescue
因為台灣太多的需要做文化的搶救的這些事物
Most of the many archaeologists came and went to serve as
大部分很多的有考古學者來去擔任
So like environmental image assessment to do EIA work
所以像環境影像評估做環評工作
Many archaeologists also participated in
也是很多考古學者參與
So in fact, archaeologists and today's society
所以其實考古學者和現在社會
In fact, there is a very close relationship between these
其實有非常密切的這些關係
So many modern issues
所以很多現代的議題
also from some different viewpoints
也可以從一些不同的觀點
to provide some thoughts
來提供一些思考
so what
那么所以呢
But how to meet the ancients
但是怎么样去和古代人相遇
how to see ancient people
怎么去看到古代的人
i want this one
我想这一个
These ancient people have disappeared
这些古代的人已经消失了
completely gone
完全都不见了
but luckily
但是所幸呢
what about these ancient people
这些古代的人呢
he walked back
他反走过
he did the opposite
他反做过
He must have left some traces
他必然会留下了一些痕迹
What about archaeologists?
那么透过考古学家呢
Through the clues of these clues
透过这些线索的蛛丝马迹的
What about these studies and these analyzes?
这些研究这些分析呢
we still
我们仍然呢
there is still a chance
还有机会呢
Can meet ancient people
可以和古代的人相遇
so this is
所以这就是
what about archaeologists
考古学者呢
a job that can be done
所可以做的一项工作
Then the data of archaeological research
那么考古学的研究的资料
probably basically
大概基本上面
mainly through the legacy of these substances
主要是透过这些物质的遗留
because the ancient people
因为古代的人
what about immaterial things
一些非物质的东西呢
has disappeared
已经消失不见了
right
对不对
because it looks like some
因为特别像一些
What can't be saved?
不能够保存的东西呢
all gone
都消失掉了
He said he could stay
他说能够留下来的呢
Basically these are these remnants of matter
基本上这些是物质的这些遗留
And inside the material
而物质里面呢
Because basically it's these
因为基本上面是这一些的
non-organic
不能够非有机职的
or non-perishable
或者是不容易腐烂的东西
to survive
才能够流存下来
This thing has become the treasure of archaeologists
这个东西也就变成了考古学家的宝贝
Archaeologists use these things
考古学家就透过这些东西
To be able to get close to these ancient humans
才能够去接近这些古代的人类
So what about our research data?
所以我们这研究的资料呢
basically contains these relics
基本上是包含这些遗物
ruins and ruins
遗迹还有遗址
These are the main materials we studied
这就是我们研究的这些主要的素材
then these things are archaeologists
那么这些东西都是考古学家
Regardless of porcelain naughty stoneware
不管磁器 淘气 石器
Regardless of the legacy of these plants, the legacy of animals
不管这些植物的遗留 动物的遗留
These are basically as long as archaeologists can discover
这些基本只要能考古学家可以发现的
It can be used as these materials for its research
它都可以作为它研究的这些素材
Then there are other so-called relics
那么另外还有一些所谓遗迹
It is some phenomena left over by ancient humans.
就是古代人类所遗留下来的一些现象
or some structure
或者一些结构
So what can be found?
那么还能够被发现的呢
it can also be important
它也可以成为很重要的
A material for archaeological research
考古学研究的一个材料
So as for the acquisition of these materials
那么至于这些材料的取得
Archaeologists are two methods
考古学家就是两个方法
an archaeological survey
一个做考古调查
The other is to do archaeological excavations
另外一个是做考古的发掘
archaeological investigation
考古调查
Just go to the wild to find it when it rains
就是到天雨到野外去找
through your pastor
可以透過你的牧師
through this drill of yours
可以透過你的這個鑽探
Even through some scientific means
甚至可以透過一些科學的手段
like this one using ground penetrating radar
像這個利用透地雷達
or other scientific means
或者其他的科學手段
Come help us find the ancients
來幫助我們去找尋古代人的
these ruins
這些遺址遺跡
or relic
或者遺物
so-called clues
就是所謂的蛛絲馬跡
able to find out
能夠找得出來
So so this part
那麼所以這個部分
I give an example
我舉個例子
Just now Vice President Wang mentioned
剛剛這個王副院長提到
We are in Tainan Science Park
我們在台南科學園區
Doing this archaeological investigation work for more than ten years
做了十幾年的這個考古調查工作
We are all through this method
我們都是透過這個方法
do research first
先做調查
through various means
而透過各種手段
including these simplest
包括這些最簡單的
just walk to observe
只是走路去觀察
some drill
有一些用鑽探
There are also some scientific
也有一些利用科學的
means of detection
探測的手段
want to discover in this area
想要發現在這個地區裡面
buried under the ground
埋藏在地底下的
The remains of these ancient humans
這些古代人類的遺留
including ruins
包括遺址遺跡
or birth relics
或者是生兒遺物
So so we're in this Nanke area
那麼所以我們在這個南科地區
just found out you see
就發現了你看
A Nanke found so many of these remnants
一個南科就發現這麼多的這些遺留
what about these ruins
這些遺址呢
It represents different worlds
它分別代表了不同世界
on this land
在这一块土地上
all these clues that flowed down
所一流下来的这些蛛丝马鸡
through this thread
透过这蛛丝马鸡
to the people of this land
可以对这块土地的人类
can have more understanding
可以有更多的一些认识
still understand
还有了解
This is our other method
这是我们另外一个方法
is to excavate
就是发掘
Some people joked about relying on scholars
有人笑话的靠过学家
You have relied on scholars
你们靠过学家
hole by hole
一个洞一个洞的
what are you doing
你们干嘛
This is called weasel burrowing
这是叫黄鼠狼打洞
Look, this is really a hole
你看这个真打洞
In fact, our hole
其实我们这个打洞
It is also a learned method
也是一种靠过学的方法
from the hole
从洞里面
to be very systematic
要去很有系统的
Take these clues of ancient humans
把古代人类的这些蛛丝马鸡
can be found systematically
能够很有系统的找出来
then do research
然后再去做研究
do patchwork
做拼凑
sorry
对不起
do you see us
你看我们是不是
Weasel has burrowed
黄鼠狼打洞了
punch so many holes
打那么多洞
You see, this hole is actually
你看这个洞其实是
are very systematic
都非常有系统的
Because the future underground
因为将来地底下的
anything
任何一个东西
We all have very detailed records
我们都有很详细的记录
it is known
我们都知道
where did this come from
这个从哪里出来的
after you come out in the future
将来你出来之后
when it comes to putting it together
要把它拼凑起来的时候
with the help of this system
就可以借助这种系统的
this program
这种程序
and can be completed
而可以加以完成
Where are we in this Greedy Science Park?
我們在這個貪婪科學園區呢
did these on a very large scale
做了非常大規模的這些
salvage these excavations
搶救這些的發掘
investigation
調查
So Chen Ru just said that Vice President Wang
所以陳如剛剛王副院長講
we have tons of these relics
我們有大量的這些遺物
So Central Court
所以中央院
He dare not let us ship back
他不敢東西讓我們運回來
after shipping back
運回來以後
He's going to help us build several houses
他要幫我們蓋好幾棟房子
this is the most difficult thing
這個是最困難的事情
I believe
我相信
then for these
那麼對於這些
These materials were unearthed
出土的這些資料
Whether it's a relic
不管是遺物遺跡
Of course our next
當然我們下一步的
we have to analyze
我們必須要去分析
to study
要去研究
If you do not analyze the research
假如不分析研究
Impossible this pair is trash
不可能這一對就是垃圾一樣
but it can never have any effect
但永遠不可能產生一些作用
Then we have to do a lot of analysis
那麼我們要做很多很多的分析
So archaeologists work very hard
所以考古學家非常辛苦
He not only went to work in the field
他不只到野外去工作
After he came back from the field
他從野外回來之後
take longer
要花更長的時間
to study
要去鑽研
to analyze
要去分析
we can go
我們才能夠去
from here
從這中間
how much to go
去多少呢
can let us understand a little bit
可以讓我們去了解一點
Aspects of Ancient Humanity
古代的人類的各個面向
Then the first one is of course
那麼第一個當然是
Do S
做年代
what the hell are we doing
我們到底這個東西
what age
什么年代的
Now there are many methods
现在目前有很多的方法
There are many scientific methods
有很多科学的方法
The most commonly used method we call carbon fourteen
这个最常用的我们叫碳十四的方法
In this method, we only need to put the ground inside
这个方法我们只要把地里面
Some guerrilla values ​​unearthed
所出土的一些游击值
Or charcoal sent to the laboratory for analysis
或者木碳送到实验室里面去做分析
Finally it can tell us
最后它可以告诉我们
what is the age of the specimen itself
这个标本本身它的年代是多少
This is by far the simplest
这个是目前我们用的最简单
And one of the most commonly used methods
而且最常用的一个方法
So help us understand the age of
所以帮助我们去了解的年代
So like we are in Tainan Science Park
所以像我们在太南科学园区
we are in different sites
我们在不同的遗址
Different time
不同的时间
A chronological sequence can be established
就可以建立起来一个年代的序列
so it's clear
所以很清楚的
Each paragraph is clearly
每一个段落都有很清楚的
these years
这些年代
There is a lot of chronological data
有很多的年代数据
allows us to map the entire region's
可以让我们对整个地区的
development of the age
年代的发展
can have a clear understanding
可以有很清楚的认识
At the same time, other methods can be used
同时可以利用其他的方法
This is what we call stratigraphy
这个是我们叫层位学的方法
inside the ruins
在靠过遗址里面
can see through layers
可以透过层位 地层
Types of items that can pass through
可以透过器物的类型
after combining the two
两个结合起来之后
in a certain layer
在某一個地層裡面
it may be a certain age
它可能是某一種年代
This part is also in our archeology
這個部分也是我們考古學裡面
often used
常常用到的
a way
一種方法
Therefore through these methods
因此透過這些方法
We can map a region's
我們可以對一個地區的
sequence of its culture
它的文化的發展序列
and some temporal changes in space
以及在空間上的一些時間的變化
can clearly list it
都可以很清楚的把它列出來
Like us in Tainan Science Park
像我們在台南科學園區
from as early as 5,000 years
可以從最早的五千年
Then come up and ask for the big benkeng culture
然後上來就要大本坑文化
Niu Chou Zi Culture
牛仇子文化
Niaosong culture
鳥松文化
Hiraya culture
希拉雅文化
The last Han culture
最後漢人文化
A clear sequence of chronological development
很清楚的一個年代發展的序列
Then each one has a time
然後每一個都有一個時間的一個
a category
一個範疇
can clearly let us know
都可以很清楚的讓我們知道
This is all through chronological analysis
這都是透過年代學的分析
established by
所建立起來的
In addition, it is very important for us to understand the ancient people
另外我們要了解古代人很重要的
our life
我們的生活
In life, the people regard time as the sky
生活裡面民以時為天
then this one
那麼這一個
So we need to understand what ancient people ate
所以我們要了解古代人吃什麼
We also have many methods for this part
那這個部分我們也有很多的方法
the best way
那最好的方法
We were able to find some evidence directly
我們能夠直接發現到一些證據
or some material
或者一些材料
Then this can tell us directly
那這個可以很直接的來告訴我們
what did he eat
當時他吃什麼東西
Like we are in Tainan Science Park
像我們在台南科學園區裡面
We found the row above
我們發現了上面這一排
all this
都是這個
As a look, the top row is
作為一看 上面這一排是
plant legacy
植物的遺留
what's in the middle of this relic
這個遺物中間有什麼
There is rice
有稻米
there is millet
有小米
melon pit
有瓜的果核
And this hard worker, etc.
還有這個苦練子等等
The remains of these many plants
這些很多的植物的遺留
these plants left behind
這些植物遺留
All why it can be preserved until now
都是為什麼可以保存到現在
because five thousand years
因為五千年的時間
it should have rotted away
它早就應該腐爛掉了
because of these things
因為這些東西
They were all burned by this carbon.
都是被這個碳燒過了
carbonized
碳化了
So carbonize this
所以碳化這個
after being charred
被碳燒過之後
turned into charcoal
變成木碳了
so it doesn't perish easily
所以它就不容易腐爛
So it can still be preserved
所以還能夠保存至今
you see we now find out
你看我們現在發現了
there are so many of these
有這麼大量的這些
these millets
這些小米
this millet
這個小米
A lot of this 90,000 pieces of millet
大量的這個九萬件的小米
This is the first time Taiwan has discovered
這台灣是第一次發現
and a lot of rice stuff
还有大量的大米这些东西
are directly reflected
都是很直接的反映出来
At that time, people could already eat these crops.
当时人的已经可以吃这些农作物了
It can eat what it wants, of course it has to grow
它可以它要吃 当然要种
it has the ability to farm
它有耕作的能力
then like another like this part
那么像另外像这一个部分
There are many kinds of direct longevity bone fish bone
有很多的各种直接的寿骨 鱼骨
These also reflect the food that some people ate at that time
这些也反映出来当时人的一些吃的这些食物
Then we will of course do some analysis on these materials
那么我们对这些材料当然会做一些分析
do some analysis
做一些分析
like this rice
像这个稻米
We did analysis like morphology
我们做了像形态学的分析
Analysis of these morphology
这些形态学的分析
Just look at its size and shape
就说看它的大小形态
can be observed
可以观察出来
An evolution of these rices at different times
在不同时间这些稻米的一个演变
Because rice it will change again
因为稻米它会再变的
its breed also changes
它的品种也会改变
This change in farming techniques
这个耕作技术的改变
It will also produce some changes in its species
也会把它的品种产生了一些变化
So change from its shape
所以从它的形态上变化
Also learn about a reimplementation of a
也可以了解一个重实现的一个
Morphological development of rice
形态学的稻米的形态学的发展
Want to see this is
想注意看这个是
about 4,500 years old
大概四千五百年的遺址
As the rice at that time looking at it
作为看它的当时稻米
so small particles so small
这么小 颗粒这么小
Then this modern we improved
然后这次现代的我们改良的
Taichung Taichung No. 9
台中胎羹9号
Taichung Taichung No. 10
台中胎羹10号
These are the rice in our modern farms
这些都是现代我们的农该厂里面的稻米
As you can see its particles are very large
作为看它的颗粒就非常的大
This represents the different breeds
这个代表说不同的品种
time difference
时间的不同
resulting in different varieties of
而产生的不同品种的
these rice
这些的稻米
These parts you need to go through our research
这些部分你都需要透过我们的研究
to find out
来加以了解
In addition, like these animals and plants are also
另外像这些动物植物也是
the bones of these animals like all of us
像我们所有的这些动物的骨骼
We all do these analyzes
我们都要做这些分析
At the same time, for each bone
同时要对于每一种骨骼
It's not just about identifying its class
它不只是要鉴定它的类别
And to identify it these animals
而且要鉴定它这些动物
the existing environment
所存在的环境
this can tell us
这个可以告诉我们
It wasn't just humans at the time
它不只是人类当时
it eats or exploits these animals
它吃或者利用这些动物
It also reflects the climate of the time
而且也反映出来当时的气候环境
because in what environment
因为在什么样的环境
what kind of animal does it have
它才会有什么样的动物
so this part
所以这个部分
must also be done in detail
也必须要做很详细的
analysis of these
这些的分析
In addition, if there is no direct evidence
另外 假如没有最直接的证据
These actual archaeological remains can be seen
可以看到这些实际的考古遗留
Then we can use many scientific methods
那么我们可以透过现在很多科学的方法
This is one of our most commonly used methods
这个我们最常用的一个方法
That is to say carbon 13 and carbon 14
就是说碳十三和碳十四的
Analysis of this stable isotope
这个稳定同位素的分析
Because these different plants
因为这些不同的植物
So about the carbon thirteen and carbon fourteen isotopes
那么关于碳十三和碳十四同位素
the constituents of the animal it is in
它所在动物体内的成分
it is different
它是不一样的
so so like this
那么所以像这个
Which can be divided into have this
其中可以分成有这个
Sorry, there is this C3 plant
对不起 有这个碳三植物
C4 plants
碳四植物
and plants in Haikou
还有海口的植物
terrestrial freshwater plants
还有陆地淡水植物
it every animal
它每一种动物
flora and fauna it's different
动植物它不一样
So if we just want to analyze what's left of these animals
所以假如我们只要分析这些动物的遗留
Find the carbon 13 and carbon 14 from inside
从里面去找出来这个碳十三和碳十四的
carbon fifteen this
碳十五的这个
The quality of so-called quiet isotopes
所谓文静同位素的这个素质
let us speculate
就可以来让我们去推测
At that time, he might have eaten a certain kind of
当时人他可能吃的某一种的
these plants
这些植物
What is the environment in which it exists?
它所存在的这个环境是怎么样
So this is all using the scientific method
所以这个都是利用科学的方法
I'm just listing one
这个我只是列出一种
In fact, there are many ways
其实有很多的这方法
can help us go
可以帮助我们去
Even if you find no direct evidence
即使是你没有发现直接的证据
From some circumstantial evidence, you can
你可以从一些间接的证据里面
Let us understand what ancient people ate
可以让我们去了解古代人吃什么东西
Then what else is it like where we live?
那么另外像我们这个住的什么
What was the life style of this ancient man?
这古代人他的生活形态是怎么样
What is the form of living
居住的形态是怎么样
The most direct evidence of this is, of course,
那这个当然最直接的证据是
we are inside the archaeological site
我们在考古遗址里面
You can dig into the houses of ancient people
可以挖到古代人的房子
we can say what house he lives in
我们可以说他住什么房子
right
对不对
So if you can't dig the house
那么假如你挖不到房子
at least you can have some relics
至少你可以有一些遗迹
like our ruins
像我们这个遗址里面
Everyone, look at this one by one
诸位看这一条一条的
one by one these little by little
一条一条的这些一点一点的
what is this
这就是什么东西
This is how the ancient people lived in the house
这就是古代人居住房屋的
The holes for the pillars he dug when he made the foundation
他做了地基的时候挖的柱子的洞
So the pillar holes can be spread out in this land
所以后来柱洞可以摊留在这个土地里面
when we dig
我们挖的时候
Everyone, be very, very careful
诸位看非常非常的小心
That's why some people say that archeology is so slow
所以有人说考古学这么慢
we are at the construction site
我们在工地里面
I'm always behind these weird hands
我往往背后就是这些怪手
wait until later
等到后面
to build a house
要盖房子
to open a factory
要开工厂
we dug very slowly
我们挖得很慢
they will scold
他们就会骂
how can you be so slow
你们怎么会那么慢呢
Actually he doesn't know
其实他不知道
we're going to dig this up
我们要把这个挖出来
this is very very slow
这个非常非常慢的
If you hurry up, you won't be able to see
你快的话就看不见了
So after digging out
所以挖出来之后
can be displayed
就可以显示出来
the house at that time
当时的房屋
About 3000 years ago
大概在3000多年前
one shot house
一拍一拍的房屋
just let us help
就可以让我们帮助
let's rebuild
我们去重建
The shape of the house at that time
当时的房屋的形态
Also in the middle of each house
另外在每一栋房子中间
and these sticks
还有这些木杖
It was the people at that time
就是当时人呢
he may be a family unit
他可能以家庭为单位
after someone died
他人死了以后
buried between this house and the house
就埋在这个房屋和房屋的中间
as look over here
作为看在这边
You see these are all buried here
你看这些都是埋在这里的
this reflects
这个反映出来
At that time the whole settlement
当时整个一个聚落的
this one by one situation
这一个一个状况
In addition, we can get from
另外就是我们可以从
the whole comprehensive
整个全面性的
chair excavation
椅子的发掘
can come to rebuild
可以来重建
The shape of the whole settlement
整个聚落的形态
this is inside a chair
这个是一个椅子里面
reflected by
所反映出来的
These houses and green sticks
这些房屋和绿的木杖
People are buried in this tomb after they die
人死了以后埋在这个坟墓
In addition, there is this suffix in the middle, I can't read clearly
另外中间有这个字尾看不清楚
there are some circle points
有一些圆圈点
These movements of houses
那叫房屋的这些移流
Stationary moving flow
驻动移流
Then the ones next to it are darker
然后旁边这些比较黑的
It's the garbage dump we're talking about
是我们讲的垃圾堆
is to dump the rubbish where it settles
就是把垃圾堆在它聚落的
We are the same now
我们现在人也是一样
Now our garbage will be thrown next to the village
现在我们的垃圾都会丢到村落的旁边去
So this represents a small village at that time
所以这个代表一个当时的一个小的村落
Its whole we can excavate through archeology
它整个的我们可以透过考古发掘
dig out
挖掘出来
After this excavation
那这个发掘出来之后
Then of course it directly reflects
那么当然就很直接的反映出来
A living form of people at that time
当时人的一个居住的一种形态
Another form of settlement
还有一个聚落的一种形态
Then, of course, we will also learn about a settlement.
那么另外当然我们也去了解一个聚落
not only its settlement itself
不只它聚落本身
and the relationship between the settlement and the surrounding environment
以及聚落和周围环境的关系
So we can also go through some theoretical discussions
所以我们也可以透过一些理论上的一些讨论
Come and learn about this settlement
来去了解到这个聚落
The relationship between the position of the chair and its surroundings
椅子的位置和周遭环境之间的关系
Why does this settlement live here
这个聚落为什么会住在这里
So what's the special reason for it's
那么它的有什么特殊的理由
This settlement will choose this location here
这个聚落会选择这个位置在这里
the various environments around and around
那周围和周边的各种不同环境
this is the relationship we're talking about
這就是我們在談論的關係
This is also called
這個也是一種叫做
our participle is called
我們分語叫做
always giving analysis
一直給予分析
This is a method of analysis
這是一種分析的方法
In addition, through some theoretical analysis, we can
另外我們可以透過一些理論上的分析
make use of economic geography
把它利用經濟地理學的
so-called middle ground theory
所謂中地理論
叫Central Place Theory
叫Central Place Theory
this section to learn about these
這個部分來了解這些
inside this area
這個地區裡面
all the different clubs
所有各個不同俱樂
relationship with each other
彼此之間的關係
with some of its reflections
以它所反映出來的一些
social meaning
社會的意義
like representing different social structures
像代表不同的社會結構
a social formation
一個社會形態
it will render different
它會呈現出不同的
These forms of these clubs
這些俱樂的這些形態
Another analysis like this social structure
另外像這個社會結構的分析
We understand that there was no society
我們了解當時不帶社會
what kind of society
到底什麼社會
Is it an egalitarian society after all?
它到底是一個平等的社會
or a stratified society
或者是有階層性的社會
This society can
這種社會可以透過
archaeological data to understand
考古資料來加以了解
look like this
像這個作為看的
this is a stick
這個是一個木杖
This stick is actually
這個木杖其實
it can tell us
它可以告訴我們
a lot about this
很多的有關於這方面
training in social structure
社會結構的訓習
like these as seen
像這些作為看的
inside these sticks
這些木杖裡面
Sorry, sorry, I don't know how to do this yet
对不起 对不起 我这个还不太操作
So, this one, these lines of recruitment are in the village
那这一个这些一句句的募仗在村落里面
then it's inside
那么它这个里面
it can get from it's this burial thing
它可以从它的这个培葬的东西
Can reflect a social status among people
可以反映出来人和人之间的一个在社会地位
or a difference in wealth using the difference
或者财富上的一种差别 用差别
In addition, it is said that some of the funeral objects it buried
另外说它培葬的一些培葬品
It can also reflect some differences between
也可以反映出来之中间的一些差别
So what about this solicitation?
所以这个募仗呢
It is a reflection of social structure
它是一个可以反映有社会结构的
a very important piece of evidence
一个很重要的一项证据
Of course there are many other evidences
当然还有很多其他的一些证据
settlement like this
像这个是聚落
Then this is the site of the Hongshan Culture in the northeast of the mainland
那这个是在大陆东北的这个红山文化的遗址
It is calculated using mathematical models
它是利用数学的模式来统计出来之后
Look at the closeness of a distance between each settlement
来看每一个聚落之间的一个距离的这个紧密度
then to distinguish
然后来区分出来
words like here
像这边的话
like this this as see this
像这个 这个作为看这个
These are different
这几个不同
What about this area?
那这一个区域里面呢
it can be divided into four pieces
它可以分为四块
Look at this one, two dollars, three dollars, four dollars
你看這一塊 二塊 三塊 四塊
Then it is reflected in the highest mathematical model
那這個最高的數學模式裡面反映出來
It is all the settlements, it is more concentrated
是所有的聚落它比較集中
The density of its entire space is very tight
它整個空間的密度非常緊密
Then this thing reflects it
那這個東西它反映出來
In this area, it is entirely within the social structure
這個區域裡面它整個在社會結構裡面
it may represent a different meaning
它可能代表一個不同的意義
Maybe it represents Japan, represents a city
說不定代表一個日本 代表一個城市
That next to it might represent the countryside, or something more remote.
那旁邊也許代表鄉村 或更偏遠的鄉村
Then this reflects the whole
那這個整個反映出來
It is an urbanized
它是一個具有城市化的
or a hierarchical
或者是一個具有階級性的 階層性的
such a social form
這樣一種社會形態
Then this is using this different method
那這個是利用這種不同的方法
We come and go to learn about some settlements of ancient humans
我們來去了解到古代人類的一些聚落的
some forms
一些形態
Then in addition, like the eleven cylinders in life
那麼另外像生活裡面十一柱形
Like this one is the best of course we are also the best
像這個一 最好當然我們也最好是
there is direct evidence
有直接的證據
It can be like this is us in Tainan Science Park
可以像這個是我們在台南科學園區裡面
found a large number of this visitor
發現了大量的這個訪人
What is this visitor doing?
訪人 這個訪人是幹什麼呢
like a spinning
像是一个纺线的
represent it spinning thread
代表它纺线
It has thread to make clothes from
它有纺线可以来做衣服
Represents that the technology of spinning thread already existed at that time
代表当时已经有纺线的这种技术
But on the other hand, it is also found that
但是另外一方面也发现这个东西
as can't see anything
作为看不出什么东西
This is a broken
这个是一个断掉了
this stick
这个棒子
a stick
一个棒子
Here are the stripes
这边是一条一条条纹
Someone read it and I said what is this
有人看完一下我说这是什么东西
He said it's called Husband Beater
他说这个叫做Husband Beater
It's a warrior's stick
就是打仗夫的棍子
because this can hit
因为这个可以打
In fact, this is a bat called bark cloth
其实这个是一个什么叫树皮布的打棒
It's made of bark cloth
就是做树皮布的
So this is what was inside our clothes
那么这个就是我们当时衣服里面
In addition to imitation
除了仿制之外
it also uses bark
它还用树皮
make bark cloth
做树皮布
There is also direct evidence of this in archaeological sites.
这个在考古遗址里面也可以发现到很直接的证据
these people are called ropes
这些人叫绳索
like this imitated line
就像这个仿出来的线
Roll it out like this and become that kind of rope
这么碾出来变成那种绳索
This is inside the archaeological site
这个在考古遗址里面
can also occasionally be found
也可以偶尔发现出来
when expectations are good
预期很好的时候
These can be preserved without rotting away
这些没有腐烂掉就可以保存下来
So these things are some
所以这些东西都是一些
about when
关于当
Some of the most direct of the time
当时的一着方面的一些最直接的
some so-called evidence some evidence
一些所谓evidence 一些证据
In addition, of course, like through some decorations on the person itself
另外当然像透过人本身上的一些装饰
Like this one inside a stick
像这个是一个木杖里面的
As a look it has a lot of shark teeth
作为看它身上有很多的鲨鱼的牙齿
This thing was a decoration at that time
这个东西它是当时的一个装饰品
ornament as look
装饰品 作为看
After it is strung together, it becomes like this
它串起来之后就变成一个这样子
An act representing the adornment of everyone at the time
代表当时人人的装饰的一种行为
This is the same
这样这个也是一样
Many utensils are also displayed
很多的器物上面也呈现出来的
These things can be used as
这些事物可以作为
At that time, I learned that it was a form of decoration at that time
当时的了解到当时的一种装饰的形态
In addition, the so-called earrings are also stuffed on the ears.
另外像耳朵上面也塞了所谓耳圈
this is an earring
这个是一种耳饰
This is all direct evidence that tells us
这都是告诉我们很直接的证据
reflect the clothing of the time
反映出来当时的衣着的装饰的
such a situation
这样一种状况
This is what we can base on various evidences
这个是我们可以根据各种证据
after putting it back together
把它复原起来之后
Humans at that time
当时的人类
This was probably around 2000
这个大概是在2000年左右的
What about humans at this time?
这个时候的人类呢
he was clumsy
他当时一拙的
such a situation
这样的一种状况
In addition, technology
另外就是工艺技术
We want ancient people how to make things
我们要古代人他怎么去做东西
Technology
工艺技术
In fact, there are quite a lot of methods
这方面其实也有相当多的方法
like making pottery
像做陶器
we can use these
我们可以透过这些
These features on pottery
陶器上的这些特征
These morphological features
这些形态上的特征
also to restore his pottery
也来复原他制作陶器的
every step
每一个步骤
This, of course, requires some analysis
这当然中间也需要透过一些分析
like the fire of these pottery
像这些陶器的烧烧的火候
and the erection of pottery, etc.
以及陶器的直立等等
can help us rebuild
都可以帮助我们去重建
At that time a technique for making pottery
当时一个制造陶器的技术
In addition, the same is true
另外实际也是一样
such a practical
这么一个实际
what is it for
它到底是做什么用途的
how it is made
它怎么制作的
It is also possible to use some experimental methods
也可以透过一些实验的方法
Then we rebuild
然后我们重建
At that time the actual
当时这个实际
its possible use
它可能的用途
this is the same
这个也是一样
this is a knife
这是一个刀子
was used to speculate
当时用来推测
probably for cutting
可能是用来割
to harvest
收割
broken
倒碎的
We can experimentally
我們可以透過實驗的方法
come help us go
來幫助我們去
through these other analytical methods
可以透過這些其他的一些分析方法
Include this analysis of utility traces
包含這個對實用痕的分析
And on the wind blade of this knife
還有這個刀的風刃上面的
These chemical analyzes of some residues
一些殘留物的這些化學分析
come help us rebuild
來幫助我們去重建
the knife itself
這個刀子本身的
the way it's used
它的使用的方法
function and the technology it makes
功能以及它製造的技術
That can also help us to
那另外也可以幫助我們去
archaeological data
考古資料
allows us to understand the ancient
可以讓我們去了解古人的
some doubts about life
一些生命的疑理
its life doubt
它的生命疑理
people know this person in his lifetime
人知道這個人在一生裡面
there will be many suspicions
會有很多的疑似
There are many suspicions of birth, old age, illness and death
種生老病死都有很多的疑似
like this from this like this
像這個從這個像這個
Most sticks inside
最多的木杖裡面
can understand when a person dies
可以了解到人死的時候
how to deal with it
怎麼去處理它
It's a deadly suspicion
這是一種死的疑似
As it looks like this is
作為看的像這個是
This is probably in
這個是大概是在
The 2,500-year-old site
2500年的這個遺址
above as seen
上面作為看得出來
This man is buried in it
這個人是埋在這裡面
Next to this is the viewing tree
旁邊這個是有這個觀木
This view has emerged
這個觀已經浮現了
But we can dig through this very carefully
但是我们可以透过这个很仔细的挖掘
Can dig out traces of its closing curtain
可以把它的关幕的痕迹挖出来
and then in the man's bones themselves
然后在这个人的骨头本身
is it lying down
它是不是躺着的
Barbarians like now are rotten people
像现在一般蛮人是它是腐趴的人
This is a common custom in this society
这个是这个社会里面一个普遍的一个习俗
so dirty
所以腐身脏
In addition to this above
另外这个上面
must be on every roof of it
在一定在它的每一个屋上面
There must be a clay pot
都一定会有一个陶罐
There's something in this clay pot
这个陶罐里面有东西在里面
We analyze some food in it
我们分析里面有一些食物
like bones chicken bones
像骨头 鸡的骨头
fish bones with food
还有食物的鱼的骨头
This is an offering
这个作为一种offering
a sacrificial
一种祭祀的
a sacrificial pottery
一种祭祀的一种陶器
above so it must be above the head of its house
上面所以它一定会在它的屋的头的上方
will put this sacrifice
会放这个祭祀
So this is one of the society at that time
所以这个是当时这个社会的一个
a common burial a custom
普遍的一个埋葬的一个习俗的
a ritual habit
一种儀式的习惯
Well so this is where we get back together
那么所以这是我们复原起来
At that time, it was probably a kind of burial, a sacrificial ritual
那当时它的大概一个埋葬的一种祭俗的
that additionally acts as
那另外作为
Everyone look at this
各位看这个是
This is a human skeleton of a woman
这是一个女性的一个人骨
You see it between the legs
各位看它在两个腿之间
and a baby
还有一个婴儿的
Have you seen
看见没有
This looks like it will be very impressive
这看来会很感动的
because of what
因为什么
because of this person
因为这个人
This woman may have had a difficult labor during labor
这个女人可能是在生产的时候难产
Both mother and child were disturbed after she was born
她生出来之后母子都不安
it's all passed away
这都过世了
so when she buried
所以她埋的时候
And put her little one in mother's
还把她的小孩子放在妈妈的
the middle of the thigh
这个大腿的中间
this child
这一个小孩子
This thing is through our archeology
这个东西都是透过我们考古学
very careful excavation
非常仔细的发掘
To be able to find this phenomenon
才能够把这种现象能够找到
able to dig out
能够发掘出来
also reflected
也反映出来
At that time, there was something about death in this society.
当时这个社会里面有关于死亡的
a treat for this matter
这件事情的一种对待
like in this amusement society
像在这游乐社会里面
A child is not treated as a person at all
小孩子根本不当做是一个人看待
So just throw it away after you die
所以死了之后就随便丢弃了
eaten by dogs
被狗吃掉了
But in this society
但是在这个社会里面
we got from another ranch
我们从别的牧场里面
He has always had great respect for children
他对小孩子一向非常的尊重
also very good
也非常好的
Even if he is a small child
他即使很小的小孩子
It also covers him very well.
也特别很好地给他掩满
Also like this man his teeth
另外像这个人他的牙齿
This is the same as Han Xi's Taiwanese aborigines
这个是韩西的台湾原住民一样
There is such a custom of tooth extraction
有打牙的 拔牙的 这种习俗
We know tooth extraction is a ritual
我们知道拔牙是一种仪式
like many adults in aboriginal
像在原住民里面很多成年里
Or one that he has military exploits
或者是一种他有战功了
he may perform some kind of ceremony
他或者会举行某种仪式
Pulling out his front teeth
拔牙他是把门齿
Second incisor Lateral incisor
第二个门齿 侧门齿
His teeth were pulled out
他的拳齿拔掉了
Such a custom is present in our aboriginal society
这样一个习俗在目前我们原住民的社会里面
In the past, there were still many tribes
过去还是很多部落里面
There is also the custom of tooth extraction
也都有拔牙的习俗
This can be found in the pastoral chapter
这个是从牧章里面可以发现
can let us understand the life at that time
可以让我们了解到当时生命一里
A manifestation of life I
的 生命一世的一种表现
In addition, what we just talked about
另外我们可以刚刚所谈到的
It's all material
都是一些物质方面的
In fact, it is spiritual
其实它心灵方面
We can pass through many material first-class
我们可以透过很多的物质一流
The same can help us to
也同样的可以帮助我们去
Restoring the manpower of the past
复原过去的人力
some leading states
一些先領的狀態
Like this from many artifacts
像這個從很多的這個器物裡面呢
We can learn about its cognitive
我們可以了解到它的這些認知的
in this respect as it does for aesthetics
這方面像它對於美學的
for aesthetic
對於審美的
such a cognition
這樣一種認知
In addition, some religious beliefs and so on are reflected
另外反映出來的一些宗教的信仰等等
In fact, many can still be obtained from material
其實很多還是可以從物質
Come and help us to rebuild
諸史馬基裡面來幫助我們去來重建
guys look like this
各位看像這個
This is what was unearthed inside our chair
這是我們這個椅子裡面出土的
These images of these faces
這些人面的這些像
Everyone, look at this, it's very cute
這個各位看這個非常可愛的
It's kind of like ET's
這有點像ET的
like space
像太空
look like a man from outer space
像外太空的人的樣子
I don't know if they've seen aliens
當時不知道他們有沒有看過外太空人
But this is the Model it made
不過這個作為它做出來的這個Model
actually very much like
其實是非常像
like this one from ET
像ET的這個樣子
like this is
像這個是
then this is a
那這個是一個
it seems we often talk
看起來我們常常講
This looks a bit like an Indian
這個有點像印度人
Everyone look at this high nose
各位看這個高鼻子
this hair
這個頭髮
like a foreigner now
像一個現在一般叫外國人
So this representative was the person at the time
所以這個代表是當時的人
his kind of difference between you and me
他的一種你我之間的一種差別
he saw these people look
他看到這些人長相
make him different
害他自己不一樣
So he made a performance in the cognition of a group of people
所以他就做出來了一種族群認知上的表現
There is also a lot of information on these
這些方面的資料也非常多
like this tomb staff
像這個墓杖也是一樣
in the whole society
整個社會裡面
in burial customs
在埋葬的習俗裡面
its cognition
它的認知
All avatars must face in one direction
所有的頭像都要朝一個方向
This picture is from the north
這個頭像是北邊
everyone look north
各位看北邊
will face north
都會朝北
in other cultures
在別的文化裡面
all facing south
所有都是朝南
Facing south
一遇朝南
This reflects the beliefs of the time
這個都是反映出來當時的信仰
maybe
說不定
like they are now muslim
就像他們現在回教
this islam
這個伊斯蘭教
So all of his people are headed towards Mai's house
所以他所有的這些人都要朝向邁家
The manifestation of such a concept
這樣一種觀念的展現
In addition, of course the substance
另外當然物質裡面
There are many transactions
有很多是交易行為
So we are in this will
所以我們在這個意志裡面
Lots of items to trade can be found
可以發現很多交易的物品
not natively generated
不是產生於本地的東西
it reflects a transaction
它反映出來就是一種交易
This deal has a short distance deal
這個交易有短距離的交易
or long-distance transactions
或者長距離的交易
able to come from far away
從很遠的地方能夠來的
or available nearby
或者很近的地方可以得到的
These things are a
這些東西都是一種
human interaction
人和人之間的互動
an act of trading
而一种交易的行为
Therefore, through the analysis of these materials
所以透过这些材料的分析
Materials like these can be analyzed from its raw material
像这些材料可以从它的原料的分析
Analysis from its place of origin
从它产地的分析
to understand the possible sources of these things
来了解到这些东西的可能来源
And the behavior of a transaction that may represent behind it
以及它背后可能代表的一种交易的行为
this part
这个部分
You can see that this is about a thousand years ago in Taiwan
大家看这个是大概台湾在一千多年的时候
These ancient humans in Taiwan had a lot of transactions with these Han people
台湾的这些古代的人类和这些汉人有很多的交易
Just saw these magnets
刚刚看到这些磁器
these peachy
这些桃气
these brass and so on
这些铜器等等
It was all obtained through a kind of exchange between the Han people
都是汉人之间的一种交易所获得的
In addition, you can also learn about the behavior of ancient humans in war.
另外还可以了解到古代人类的战争的行为
let's watch
我们注意看
The most direct evidence of this is that we can get
这个最直接的证据是我们可以从人骨上面
Pay attention to this sentence, human bones
注意看这一个这句人骨
It looks pretty pitiful at first
是先看起来蛮可怜的
so it's on
所以它身上
this is this look at this thing
这是这个注意看这什么东西
it's an archery arrow
这是一个射箭的箭
arrow
箭头
These arrows shot under this leash of it
这些射箭射在它的这个勒骨的下面
In addition, it also had a kind of wound on its lumbar spine
另外在它的这个腰椎上面也中了一种
Then he was hit by an arrow on the hand bone of the lower limb bone of this hand
然后在他的这个手的下肢骨的手骨上面也中了一箭
So he has an arrow in his waist
所以他身上还有在他的腰部分也有一箭
so he got hit by several arrows
所以他中了好几箭
This represented a conflicting behavior at the time
这代表当时的一种冲突的行为
Of course in ancient times these wars
当然在古代这些战争
In fact, he may not really be a war
其实他未必真正是战争
some are rituals
有一些是仪式
like this beheading thing
像这个砍头的事情
In fact, he must represent
其实他必定代表了
So it must be a conflict between the two ethnic groups
所以必然是两个族群的冲突
He sometimes represents a ritual
他有时候是代表一种仪式
Beheading like this represents being in a society
像这个砍头是代表在一个社会里面
he has a special ritual
他具有一种特殊的仪式
a meaning
一种意义
like this guy too
像这个人也是一样
As a look at him too
作为看他身上也是
There's a suspicious arrow here
这边有一个摄疑箭
Here the head was chopped off
这边头上被砍掉了
This head is gone
这个头已经被不见了
head cut off
头砍掉了
Then this hand shot an arrow here
然后这个手这里也是摄了一箭
There is an arrow here
这边有箭头在这里
Have you seen
看见没有
the head is missing
这边头是不见了
This represents a kind of
这个代表当时的一种
conflict or war
衝突或者是戰爭的這種行為
But we are in Taiwan
但是我們在台灣的
I have been doing archaeology for so long
我做過這麼長久的考古
tell the truth
說實在話
Our Ancient Ancestors in Taiwan
我們台灣古代的先人
he is very peaceful
他非常和平的
We did not find any
我們並沒有發現有任何的
This situation of mass killing
大量的殺戮的這種情況
Occasionally, one or two things like this are found
偶爾就是發現這樣一兩件
This body was beheaded
這種身上被砍頭了
Or just one or two
或身上中了一兩件而已
We have not found such a million species
我們並沒有發現像這種萬人種
Or the situation of mass killings
或者大集體殺戮的這種狀況
Basically it's pretty peaceful
基本上面還是相當和平的
such a society
這麼一個社會
Everyone saw this just now
各位看的這個剛剛的這個
This is what we round up
這個就是我們附圓起來
probably it's here
大概它在這個
this is from the front
這個是從前面
from the tip of the shot
是從射的尖上面
This is the sign shot from behind
這個是從背後射的這個標
or an arrow shot it to death
或者箭把它射死掉的
Then cut off the head
然後把頭就割掉了
cut off the head
把頭割下來
wrap hands
裹手
In addition, for these diseases of ancient people
另外我們對於古代人的這些疾病
physical condition can also be
身體狀況也可以透過
These archaeological data to explain
這些考古資料來解釋
like this through this person
像這個透過這個人
We can understand the symptoms of many diseases
我们可以了解很多的疾病的病征
like the most common
像最常见的
Easiest to see is dental disease
最容易看的是牙齿的疾病
everybody look
各位看
This is also dental disease
这个也牙齿的疾病
The one here is called Nongyang
这边的这个叫做农阳
Its tooth root can run this way
它的齿根可以跑到这边来的
see it doesn't
看它没有
Then of course cast teeth
然后当然铸牙
this is the most common
这是最常见的
this asian disease
这个亚洲病
This is the most common disease
这是最常见的疾病
Also like here
另外像这边
There's a tumor here
这边有一个肿瘤
This man has a large tumor on his head
这个人头上面长了一个大的肿瘤
The other most common is this
另外最常见的是这个
Herniation of this vertebral disc
这个椎尖盘的突出
like this
像这个
we talk about this
我们讲这些
We usually talk about bone spurs
我们一般讲骨刺
In addition to the bone itself
另外对骨头本身的
these anemias
这些贫血症
This nutritional deficiency and so on
这个营养不足等等
can pass through these human bones
都可以透过这些人骨上面
to understand
来加以理解
This also reflects
这个也反映出来
Not just the state of human health at the time
不只是当时人类的健康状况
It also reflects the nutritional status of the
也反映出来当时的营养状况
It also reflects the environmental conditions at that time
也反映出来当时的环境状况
some things about many, many ancient people
很多很多的古代人的一些事情
so these
所以这些
so this aspect
所以这个方面呢
there are many
有很多的
provide us with an understanding of ancient humans'
提供我们去了解古代人类的
a lot of these
很多的这些
these about health
这些关于健康
environment nutrition
环境 营养
and its labor
以及它的劳力
Some are too tired
有的太操劳了
will also be left on the body
也会在身上留下了
many of these traces
很多的这些痕迹
so this part
所以这一部分呢
can also
也可以
These are very precious materials
都是非常珍贵的这些资料
can now also understand
现在还可以了解到
Did Ancient People Have Lung Disease?
古代人是不是有肺病
TB
TB
punch the bone
冲骨头上面
You can also learn about infectious diseases, etc.
也可以了解传染病等等
in addition
另外
Finally we want to understand
最后我们想要去了解
what do you want to look like
大家要长什么样子
what does it look like
它的面相怎么样
Now we also have many ways
现在我们也有很多的方法
The most traditional method now
现在最传统的方法
Just use these human bones
就是利用这些人骨
We can see us as human bones
我们可以作为看我们这些人骨
we can
我们可以
find a human skull
发现一个人人头骨
We can now take advantage of advanced equipment
我们现在可以利用先进的设备
This is 3D scanning
这就3D扫描
ready to print
可以来列印
So 3D printing
所以3D列印
can take this man to the bone
可以把这个人骨头
can print it out
可以把它列印出来
become like this
变成这样子
become this
变成这个
a mold comes out
一個模子出來
Then put this mold
然後把這個模子
and then remolding
然後再經過翻模
turned into a
翻模之後變成一個
A rice in a mold inside
一個飯在一個模在裡面
Then above this we pass through
然後這上面我們再透過
This so-called muscle filling
這個所謂肌肉的填補
This muscle filling is not random filling
這個肌肉填補不是隨意填補
must be based on a lot of data
必須要根據很多的資料
Through anatomical data
透過解剖學的資料
to learn about different races
來了解到不同的人種
the probable thickness of its muscles
它的肌肉的可能的厚度
and muscle growth
以及肌肉的生長的狀況
Then according to this thing
然後根據這個東西
Let's do some muscle filling
我們來做一些肌肉的填補
Finally we can have some
最後我們可以有一些需要
archaeological art
叫做考古藝術的
This person is here to help us
這個人才來幫助我們
to restore
去復原
contains its hair
包含它的毛髮
hair eyebrows
頭髮 眉毛
whole face etc.
整個面容等等
to restore
來加以復原起來
This is in our Tantan Science Park
這個是在我們潭潭科學園區的
A skull from about 5,000 years ago
大概五千年前的一個頭骨
Finally we based on these skulls
最後我們根據這些頭骨
can be recovered
可以復原出來
A face of the possible length at that time
當時的可能長的一個面貌
what kind of thing
是什麼樣的東西
so we do quite a bit
所以我們做的相當多
We can be in different times
大家可以在不同的时代
These human bones of us in different times
不同的时代我们的这些人骨
Finally recovered
最后复原出来
This was about a thousand years ago
这个大概是在一千多年以前的
Ancient humans in Taiwan
台湾的古代人类
You see, she looks a little prettier
你看看起来好像长得比较漂亮一点
this is a female
这个是一个女性
these a male
这些一个男性
Well, this is when they
那么这个是当时他们
after death
死后之后
Human bones look like this
人骨的人的骨头是这样子
This is also through some scientific methods
这个也是透过一些科学的方法
restore it
把它复原起来
now there is another way
现在还有别的方法
computer simulation, etc.
可以利用电脑模拟等等
to restore the face of ancient people
来复原古代人的面貌的一个
a look
一个长相
Then finally we can put all
那最后我们可以把所有的
Eleven aspects of these materials are annotated
这些资料十一注行各方面
war its society and more
战争它的社会等等
can put the whole time
可以把整个当时
the face of human life
人类的生活面貌
to do a comprehensive
来做一个全面性的
such a recovery
这样的一个复原
so in addition
所以另外呢
That is, we can also understand the human environment at that time
就是我们也可以了解当时人类的环境
What was the living environment like at that time?
当时居住的环境到底是怎么样
This we can use through
这个我们可以透过
Analysis of Soil by Valley
靠谷以指的土壤的分析
The strict detective of the earth's core and so on
土壤的地心的严辛的专探等等呢
to do these analyzes
來做這些分析
But it's impossible for me to go into detail here
但這我不可能在這裡細講
Then this part can come and let us rebuild
那這個部分可以來讓我們重建
The environments that humans faced at that time
當時人類它所面對的這些環境
Of course, this environment can also include the
當然這環境裡面也可以包含剛剛講過的
Through animal legacy, plant legacy, etc.
透過動物的遺留 植物遺留等等
to tell us about the circumstances
來告訴我們當時的環境
like the weather
像氣候狀況怎麼樣
but what about the season
但當時的季節狀況怎麼樣
and the nearby surrounding landforms at that time
以及當時的附近的周遭的地貌
what is the terrain like
地形是怎麼樣的
can help us recover
都可以幫助我們去做復原
Then this is in our solar science park
那這個是在我們太陽科學園區
Through this extended new expert
透過這個延新的專探
Taking Soil Analysis
以土壤的分析
we can come back
我們可以來復原起來
The location of Nanke at that time
當時的這個南科的這個位置
In fact, where was the scope at that time?
其實當時的範圍在哪裡
here is the sea
這邊都是海
At that time the settlement has been here
當時這個聚落一直在這裡
it's all by the sea
它就全在海邊
there are people who live by the sea
還有人就住在海邊
This is right next to the beach for living
這個就緊接著海邊來做居住
But now you can see
但是現在 大家可以看
As a mainlander from Tainan, you know
作為大陸的台南人就知道
This is Qigu
這個是七谷
Currently at the beach
現在目前在海邊
Now Nanke's work is in the sea
那現在南科的作為滄海
in sea field
在海上田
It's 20 kilometers away
这边距离已经20公里了
time difference of 5000 years
差别5000年的时间
The sea was still here in 5000 years
在5000年的时候海边还在这里
around here in about 3000
大概3000年的时候大概在这里
now the beach
现在目前海边
the coast is here too
海岸也在这里
Qigu
七股
Yantian on Qigu's side is here
七股这边的沿田都在这里
So the distance between them is more than 20 kilometers
所以这中间的距离已经超过20公里
So we talk about sea fields
所以我们讲沧海上田
But this can be found through our archaeological research
但是这个可以透过我们考古学的研究
You can also do something based on the environment at that time
可以把当时的环境也可以来做一些
these endowments
这些赋源
In addition, of course we have to understand a culture
另外当然我们要去了解一个文化
Ancients and his relationship
古代人他的关系
what is his source
他的来源怎么样
where did he come from
他到从哪里来的
This part is inside archeology
这个部分在考古学里面
It is also possible to use these typological comparisons
也可以透过这些类型学的比角
The ratio angle of these vapors
这些汽雾的比角
Now through the comparison of the DNA of the crowd
现在可以透过人群的这些DNA的比角
There are also animals raised in living things, etc.
还有生物里面所鸳养的动物的等等
You can come to know the source of these people
可以来了解到这些人的源头
where the hell
到底在哪里
This is in Tainan Academy of Sciences area
这个是在台南科学院区
5000 years ago
5000年前的
This human speculates about his origin
這個人類推測他的來源
After comparing these analyzes
透過這些分析比較之後
His source is from
他的來源是來自於
Probably from south of Fujian to Hainan Island
大概是在福建一南到海南島
up this coast
在這個海岸上面這一帶
It is probably between the culture of Taiwan 5,000 years ago
大概是和台灣五千年前的文化之間
very close relationship
非常密切的關係
their source
他們的源頭
Their home probably came from this place
他們的老家可能就來自於這個地方
This can also be told through these data
這個也是可以透過這些資料來告訴我們
In addition, the relationship between people
另外就是人和人的關
In addition to the typological comparison on this artifact
除了這個器物上的類型學的比較之外
Now this is also
現在目前也是這個
The so-called genetic analysis and comparison of this ethnic group
所謂這個族群遺傳的分析比較
then this aspect
那麼這個方面
We've actually done a lot so far
我們其實目前做了很多
That's us in Nanke
那是我們在南科
This is a site of the Three Treasures
這個三寶族一個遺址
DNA extracted from his bones
他的人骨上面所萃取的DNA
come to know these people
來了解到這些人
where he may have been a source
他可能的一個來源的地方
and genetic relationships with other populations
以及和其他人群之間的遺傳上的關係
In addition, through these human bones themselves,
另外也可以透過這些人骨本身的
Some of his measured features
他的一些測量性的特徵
Some measured features can also be used to understand the relationship between each other
一些測量性的特征也可以來了解到彼此之間的關系
So this aspect is also very important in archaeology.
所以這方面也是考古學裡面很重要的
To understand the relationship between people and people
要去了解人群和人群之間的關系
This is a very important means
這是一個很重要的一些手段
this is what we do
這個是我們在做的
Our knowledge quiz in January
上了一月份的我們的知識想驗
Professor Chen Zhongyu's work on guiding people
陳忠育教授所做的量導人的
This is the Marx Planck Institute in Germany
所利用這是德國的Marx Planck研究所
The DNA they made out of the Quantitative Humans
他們對量導人股所做出來的DNA的
genetic analysis
遺傳的分析
Discover the haploids inside
發現裡面的單倍體
The so-called 10,000 haploid
所謂1萬的單倍體
its distribution throughout the region
它在整個地區裡面分佈的狀態
This can also give us some clues
這個也可以告訴我們一些線索
movement of these people
這些人群的移動
direction of movement
移動的方向
source of movement etc.
移動的來源等等
so
所以
Mainly to introduce to you
主要是給各位介紹一下
How Archeology Gets Closer to the Ancients
考古學怎麼去接近古人
It's easy for us modern people
我們這個現代人很容易
meet every day
每天見面
But the ancient people actually
但是古代的人其實
Must go through these archaeological crowns
必須要去透過這些考古加冕
Among the data unearthed
所挖掘出來的這些資料裡面
then bit by bit
然後點點滴滴的
Through these clues
透過這些蛛絲馬跡
Let's turn the life of ancient human beings into
讓我們去把人類古代人的生活面向
slowly piece it together
慢慢的把它拼湊起來
How much can we finally know
最後我們多少可以認識的
What was the condition of the ancient people?
古代的人到底他的狀況是什麼樣
Of course he won't stand up and argue to me
當然他不會站起來給我argue
He won't stand up and say you're wrong
他不會站起來說你就不對
But I guess it's all archeology itself
但是我想這都是考古學本身
He must be a scientific
他必須是一個科學性的
what he made
他做出來的東西
Must conform to some scientific principles
必須要去符合一些科學的原則
some level of science
一些科學的水準
Then like this
然後這樣子的話
Then I think the ancients
那我想古代人
Even if he is lying on the ground
他即使躺在地底下
He won't come to protest
他也不會去來抗議
Then the following because of the relationship of time
然後這個下面因為時間的關係
so I
我就
Now I'm going to put some of what we've put together
現在我就把我們所拼湊起來的一些東西
Let me tell a few stories about ancient people
我來講幾個古代人的故事
this story
這個故事
Then this is what we do in so many archaeological works
那這個就是我們在那麼多考古工作裡面
I just picked a few out
我就挑了幾個出來
Maybe you are more interested
也許大家比較有興趣
or more concerned
或者比較關心
Let me give you a brief report
來給大家稍微做一個報告
The first one is the legend of the black ditch
第一個是黑水溝的傳奇
We know the Black Ditch, everyone knows
我們知道黑水溝大家都知道
This one is the Penghu Trench
這一個就是澎湖海溝
This is between Penghu and Taiwan
這個就是在澎湖和台灣之間的
Probably from this part of Penghu
大概從澎湖的這個部分
To the south until the waters of southern Taiwan
向南邊一直到台灣南部的海域
There is a strong, diffuse sea
有一個堅壯的、擴散的海域
The sea water depth is about 60 meters to about 100 meters
海域的海水深度大概是60米到大概100多米
such a depth
這樣的一個深度
very famous recently
最近非常有名
I just told our vice president
我剛剛給我們副院長講說
One day news in Taiwan
在台灣有一個一天的消息
then it's gone
然後就沒有了
But there is a lot of news abroad
可是在國外有很多的消息
famous foreign magazines
國外有名的雜誌
There are many journals that are still being discussed
有很多的journal上面都還在討論
I also saw a Filipino magazine yesterday
我昨天還看到一個菲律賓的雜誌
still discussing this issue
還在討論這個問題
This was here a few days ago
這個是前幾天在這個
Probably a few weeks ago
應該是前幾個禮拜吧
The Department of Natural Sciences in Taichung
這個台中的自然科學部
Dr. Zhang Junxiang in the museum
在博物館張君祥博士
He did a press conference to publish
他做了一個記者會來發表了
Said they were in the waters of Penghu
說他們在澎湖的海域裡面
one of the found
所發現的一具的
This is the so-called Xia Hangu
就是這個所謂的下韓古
This is the jaw
就是這個下巴古
jaw of a man's jaw ancient
下巴的一個人的下巴古
Well, everyone, look at Chin Bagu
那麼這個各位看著下巴古
it's very primitive
它非常的原始
Can't see
看得沒有
words like ours
像我們的人的話
Our current people are relatively slender
我們現在的人它是比較纖細的
Do you see this?
這個看得沒有
it's very out of shape
它非常的出狀
And the whole assault was very obvious
而且整個的突擊非常的明顯
because of its teeth
因為它的牙齒
Everyone looks very big
各位看非常大
this is its old tooth
這是它的舊齒
this is very big
這個非常大
then grind hard
然後磨得很厲害
Then such a lower Russian ancient
那麼這樣的一個下俄古
Then Dr. Zhang Junxiang
那麼張君祥博士
then he speculates
那麼他推測
His age should be around 190,000 years
他的年代應該是在19萬年
to 450,000 years
到45萬年之間
Of course his age
當然他這個年代
not quite sure yet
還不是十分的確定
because he is using this
因為他是利用這個
Human Lower Russian
人类的下俄古的
Buddha contained in the upper
上面的里面所包含的佛
Buddha and that
佛还有那
its two elemental composition
它两个元素的成分
Then Bijiao is in the same sea area
然后比角在同一个海域里面
unearthed hound's
所出土的猎狗的
a sea duck
一个叫海鸭
It's on the Hound
就是猎狗上面的
its relative angle
它的比角
two almost similar branches
两个几乎是类似的树枝
Then this hunting dog is probably in East Asia
然后这个猎狗大概在东亚地区
the age of its existence
它存在的年代
should probably exist in
应该是大概存在在
About 300,000 to 400,000 years
大概三四十万年
will probably disappear in the future
大概在以后就消失了
So the evidence thus becomes the inference
所以因此这个证据就变成来推论
This one is from Lower Russia
这一个下俄古的
evidence of its age
它的年代的证据
So Dr. Zhang also infers that this age is 190,000 years
所以张博士他也推论这个年代在19万年
that's all
以上
About 450,000 years or less
大概到45万年以下
such an age
这样的年代
Of course we don't care now
当然我们现在不论
regardless of this
顾不论这个
Is the age correct?
年代到底是不是正确
Then this lower Russia
那么这个下俄古
Of course, from its shape
当然从它的形态上看起来
it is a very
它就是一个非常
ancient
古老的
very primitive of a human
非常原始的一个人类的
That's why Dr. Zhang Junxiang called it a Bloomberg Yuanren
所以张军祥博士就把它称为叫做彭博元人
So he thinks that this person's closest relative is in Anhui in the mainland
所以他认为这个人他的最近的一个亲戚跟在大陆的安徽
Anhui Youming and Xianyuan people
安徽有叫和宪元人
This is in the range of 500,000 to 300,000 years for the Xianyuan people
这和宪元人的年代大概是50万年到30万年的范围里面
So he thinks there is a relationship between the two
所以他认为这两者之间有关系
So of course it caused a lot of discussion after it was published.
所以这个发表之后当然就引起了很大的一个讨论
Especially in some foreign publications in this anthropological field
特别是在国外的这个人类学界的一些刊物上面
There is a lot of discussion on this
有很多的这方面的讨论
Some people think it's too early
有人认为这个年代太早
It's too early because it's unlikely
这个太早了 因为不太可能
Why? Because in this East Asian region
为什么呢 因为在这个东亚地区
Especially in Southeast Asia
特别是这样在东南亚地区
Now on an island called Floris in Indonesia
现在在印尼的一个叫Floris島上面
The remains of a so-called very primitive human were also found
也发现了一个一个所谓非常原始的一个人类的遗骸
Then his age is 18,000 years
那么他的这个年代就18000年
so their their this
所以他们的他们这个
this man is very small
这个人长得非常小
so is a very small one
所以是一个非常小的一个
a so-called Homo erectus
一个所谓直立人
So the original person is such a
所以原人这样一个
So what is the relationship between
那么这个到底中间关系怎么样
Therefore, further discussion is required
所以都目前还需要进一步地去讨论
Then this is Wazuhara
那么这个就是和线原人
This is the Hexian original man found in Hexian, Anhui
这是在安徽的和线所发现出来的和线原人
So Dr. Zhang Junxiang put the lower frontal bone
那么所以张军乡博士就把那个下额骨
with this person
和这一个人
So I think it's the same related two people
所以认为是同一个有关系的两个人
He thinks it was probably during the Ice Age
他认为大概在冰河时代
at that time
当时那个时候
it's cold
天很冷
in the ice age
在冰河时代
Humans moved from north to south to a warmer place
人类从北方南下到一个比较暖的地方
Taiwan's Penghu area
台湾这个澎湖一带
It should be relatively warm
应该相对起来比较暖的
so hard to run
所以跑得难过来
so this person
所以这个人
He has remained in this place
他就一直保持了在这个地方
keep his original shape, a state
保持他原来的一个形貌的一个状况
Then this is the so-called Penghu Haidu
那么这就是这个所谓澎湖海度
between Penghu and Taiwan
就在澎湖和台湾之间的
Then this Dr. Zhang Junxiang
那么这个张军乡博士
Dr. Lilac said that this specimen came from this trench
丁香博士他说这个标本是来自于这个海沟
And then this specimen was actually supposedly picked up by a fisherman
然后这个标本事实上是据说是渔民捞起来的
fisherman salvaged
渔民打捞起来的
Later it was sold to a shareholder
后来是卖给了一个这个股东商
Then what about their science center?
后来他们这个科普馆呢
I asked him to buy it from the shareholder again.
又从股东商里面就又又请他又买过来了
I thought it was important so I bought it
觉得很重要就买过来了
So this is not a scientific discovery
所以这个并不是一个科学的一个发掘出来的
or scientific research
或者科学调查出来的
It is basically a point and a
它基本上面还是一个点于是一个
a second hand an acquired
一个第二手的一个获得的
such a data
这样一个资料
Well, this is the so-called Taiwan Strait
那么这个是这就是所谓的台湾海峡
What about looking at the Taiwan Strait?
作为看台湾海峡呢
This was about 18,000 years ago
这个大概是在一万八千年前
It's basically land here.
这边基本上都还是陆地
We know that after 18,000 years
我们知道一万八千年以后呢
Eighteen thousand years from now, the Ice Banner will end
就就离现在一万八千年冰旗结束了
after the end
结束后了
Then the sea level slowly rises
然后海水面慢慢的上升
so until now
所以一直到现在呢
we become the taiwan strait
我们变成台湾海峡
But eighteen thousand years ago
但是在一万八千年以前呢
This is basically the situation here
这边基本上是这个状况
This is still a situation next to a continent
这个还是一个大陆旁的状况
So this just said this
所以这个刚刚讲的这个
The origin of Penghu is located in
澎湖原点的位置是在
In the sea area, apart from the Penghe injustice just mentioned
在海域里面其实除了刚刚讲过的蓬河冤人之外
In fact, a large number of these large non-human fossils have been found in the past
其实过去发现大量的这些大型不如类的化石
Most of these fossils are fishermen
这些化石大部分都是渔民
Because this sea area is very deep, about 60 meters, 90 meters to 120 meters
因为这个海域很深 大概到60米 90米到120米
This is very deep, generally like our underwater archaeology
这个非常深 一般的像我们水下的考古的话
we can't go down this deep
我们没有办法下得这么深去
So a lot of fishermen get off their net
所以很多渔民他脱网 他传经过这里脱网
After getting off the net, except for a lot of live fish jumping around
脱网以后除了很多活泵乱跳的渔子之后
There are a lot of things that can't jump, these big things
还有很多是不会跳的 这些大的东西
So the local fishermen are scared
所以当地的渔民很害怕
At first, I was very scared and felt that there was a bad omen.
当初很害怕觉得有不祥之兆
So there are some throwing there and putting it next to the temple and throwing it there
所以有一些把丢到那里放在庙的旁边丢到那里
dare not ask him
不敢要他
Later, after some of these antiquities dealers or fossil collectors discovered
后来有一些这些古物商或者是化石的蒐集者发现之后
I think this is a treasure, so I started to collect this thing
觉得这是宝贝 所以就开始去蒐集这个东西
So now become a water boat
所以现在就变成水藏船高
So it becomes very valuable
所以就变成很值钱的东西
So now many fishermen are constantly
所以现在很多渔民不断的
You can also find it while fishing
在捕鱼过程里面还可以找到
This is a captain named Hong in Penghu
这个是在澎湖的一个船长叫洪船长
one of his boats
他的一条船
He often fishes in the sea
他经常在海域捕鱼
He often gets these
他又经常的就捞到这些
These things that used to be considered bad omens
这些过去认为是不祥之兆的东西
Now he's a baby
现在他被当成宝贝了
So a whole warehouse in his house
所以在他家里面一个整个倉库
all of these
全部都是这些的
as look
作为看
as see this is he fishing
作为看这个是他钓鱼
he can fish
他钓鱼可以钓上来
A lot of fun
很好玩
he fished
他钓鱼钓上去
catch a bone
钓上来是一个骨头
not a fish
不是一条鱼
But he also caught a fish
但是他也钓到一条鱼了
This is the archeology of water effect that we did
这是我们就做的水效考古
Follow him to investigate
也跟着他一起去做调查
This is our boat in the black ditch
这是我们在黑水沟的船上面
a condition of our trawl
我们拖网的一个状况
This is where we do our research
这是我们做调查的位置
As you can see, this is Baisha Island in Penghu
作为看这是澎湖白沙岛
This is the main island of Penghu
这是澎湖本岛
approximate location
大概发现的位置
probably at this position
大概在这个位置上面
This is the GPS we passed
这是我们经过的GPS
then do the research
然后做调查
You can find out exactly where these fossils were unearthed here
可以确切这些化石出土的位置在这里
The location of the water is here
出水的位置在这里
All of our locations are detailed
我们的所有位置都有很详细的
Latitude and longitude satellite positioning
经纬度的卫星定位
Ding Wei, we also think we should do some science
丁伟 这是我们也觉得我们应该要做一些科学的
not just fishermen
也不能只靠渔民
We're going to do some scientific research on these
我们要做一些科学的这些调查
Then this is the Captain Red just mentioned
那这个是刚刚讲的红船长
he is very funny
他非常好玩
He said fishing caught fossils
他说钓鱼钓了化石
One day, a fish will be caught
就会有一天果然钓了一条鱼上来
as look
作为看
So it's a fish, right?
所以这是一条鱼 对不对
That's what he caught
那这个是他钓起来的
It turns out he can't jump this fish
结果发现这个鱼他不会跳
right
对不对
As a look it's a fossil fish
作为看这是一个化石鱼
so this is very fun
所以这个非常好玩
he is very happy
他自己很高兴
Look at the net tied fish caught fish fossils
你看下网绑鱼钓到鱼化石
that this
那这个
This is fishing
这个是钓了
he has lots and lots of these
他有很多很多的这些
larger than class
大型不如类的
Contains big cattle
包含有大的牛
big horse
有大的马
these deer
这些鹿
these bones are very
这些骨头非常多
look
你看
This is his casual trip to sea
这个是他随便出海一趟
You can fish so many things up
就可以钓出来这么多东西上来
These people this is a big
这些人家这个是一个大的
this may be a
这个可能是一条
look at this big buffalo
你看这个很大的一个水牛的
This lower goose bone tooth
这个下鹅骨牙齿
Just to see these deer bones
就是为看这些鹿的骨头
this is very, very much
这个非常非常多
So he has a big warehouse at home
所以他家里有一大仓库
a big warehouse
一大倉庫
my game is highly recommended
我的游戏很建议
I would like to speak to our Vice President Wang
我想讲建议我们的王副院长
Can you buy it?
可以把它收购过来吧
baby
宝贝
he put it in the warehouse
他放在倉庫里
I really think it's a waste
实在是我觉得是浪费
like that
那样子
This is the Kebao Museum in Taichung
这个是台中的科保馆
Science and Security Museum
科保馆
This is when they based on these words
这个是他们根据这些话时
recovered
所复原出来的
you see this is a
你看这个是一个
a grimtooth
一个古灵齿像
This is such a high image
这个作为那么高的一条像
this thing
这东西
And this is a German buffalo
还有这个是一个叫做德式水牛
It's all based on these bones
这都是根据这些骨头
restored
复原起来的
It's all very big love is not as tired
这都是非常大的爱情不如累
these animals in the past
这些动物在过去
When the Taiwan Strait was still land
台湾海峡还是陆地的时候
are in a lot
都是在非常多
very large number of representatives
代表数量非常大
see this as
作为看这个
Just a random tune is so much
刚刚随便一调就那么多
So on behalf of the time here is a
所以代表当时的这边是一个
Probably grassland or some woods
大概是草原或者一些树林
So the animals at that time were all roaming around here.
所以当时的动物就都在这边游荡
so why
那么为什么呢
because at that time this
因为当时这个
northern ice age
北方冰期时代
It's still too cold in the north
北方还是太冷了
So the animals are going south
所以动物都是往南走
So just in Taiwan
所以刚好在台湾
just a little warmer
就稍微暖和一点
They have another source of water here
他们在这边又有水源
Forests and grasslands live here
树林又草原就在这边生活
But these animals are not actually
但是这些动物里面其实并不是
its own and at ease
它自己又有自在的
it has an enemy behind it
它背后有一个敌人
what enemy
什么敌人
there were humans
当时有人类
humans and animals together
人类和动物在一起的
what are these humans doing
这些人类干嘛
of course it has bad intentions
它当然不怀好心
to kill them
要杀他们的
to suffer
要受烈的
Watch carefully
注意看
we are in the bones
我们在骨头里面
You can find this trace
可以发现注意看这一条痕迹
What is this trace?
那这个痕迹是什么东西呢
cut by man
是人切割的
humans want to cut
人类想要切割
cut off the deer foot
把这个鹿脚切断了
to be its tool
来作为它的工具
as it is clear from here
作为看这边很清楚
This one is on top of this skinny bone
这个是在这个瘦骨上面
There are traces of this cut
有这个切割的痕迹
It's clearer here
这边更清楚了
this is a deer foot
这是一个鹿脚上面
chopped
用砍的
use a sharp tool
用很厉的工具
Said to cut off this cut
说砍下来的这个砍痕
So this thing represents
所以这个东西代表
It wasn't just animals
当时并不只是动物而已
there were humans
当时是有人类的
Humans at that time
当时人类
Well it's this human
那么它的这个人类
What is the age?
到底年代怎么样呢
Well past the Museum of Natural Sciences
那么过去自然科学博物馆
Games that used these painters themselves
曾经利用这些画师本身的游戏
what about his strategy
他的策略呢
It's reversed again
又系反侧连了
It was found that at this age
结果发现到这个年代
probably in
应该大概是在
between 10,000 and 20,000 years ago
一万多年到两万多年之间的
such an era
这样一个年代
About 10,000 to 20,000 years
一两万年大概
At most about 30,000 years
最多大概就是三万年
But they have been doing it on the mainland for 40,000 years
但是他们大陆做了四万年
such an era
这样一个年代
In this era and just now Dr. Zhang Junxiang
这个年代和刚刚的张军祥博士
The age of Peng Huyuan mentioned is very different.
所讲的彭护元人年代就差了很大了
So it was hundreds of thousands of years ago
所以那个年代十几万年
This is 10,000 to 20,000 years
这个就一两万年
Then this makes a big difference
那么这个就差别就非常大
So this problem should not be solved yet
所以这个问题应该还没有解决
Are those fossils that old?
到底那些化石有没有那么早
So what age is it
那么它到底年代
Is it possible to further determine
可不可以更进一步的去确定
This requires the future
这方面都需要未来
More of these scientific investigations are needed
还需要更多的这些科学调查工作
So like our underwater valley work
所以像我们的水下靠谷工作
Currently working on the sea
目前也在做海域
We also hope to find
我们也希望可以发现到
For some more information on this
有关更多的这方面的一些讯息
At the same time we also seek to understand
同时我们也去了解
What was its environment like at that time?
它当时的环境到底面貌是怎么样
Because it's 80 meters underwater 90 meters
因为在水下80公尺 90公尺
we can't see
我们看不见
but we can use these deep sea
但我们就可以利用这些深海的这些
What about the equipment for taking pictures?
照相的这些设备呢
Let's observe the sea at that time
我们来观察当时的海面
what is it like
到底是怎么样的
what is its terrain like
它的地貌是怎么样
That's what we have to do
那这方面也是我们要去做
an object of study
研究的一个对象
then this is
那这个是
This is really human
这是真的有人类了
This is in Fujian
这是在福建的这个
What about this part of the sea?
这个部分的海域里面呢
found
发现到了
in the Taiwan Strait
在台湾海峡海域里面
have found this human
有发现到这个人类的
this one
这一个
Watch carefully
注意看
femur
大腿骨的
This one is old
这一个骨旧的
this part
这个部分
it's a human
这是一个人类的
So the rep says
所以这个代表说
was
当时是
Not just the discovery of tools made by humans
不只是发现到人类所制造的工具
say cut bones
来说切割的骨头
And there are also human discoveries
而且本身也有人类的发现
So the rep says
所以这个代表说
What about in this sea area?
这个海域里面呢
About 10,000 to 20,000 to 30,000 years
大概在一万年到两万年三万年的时候
Indeed, there are humans
的确也有人类居住
There are also lots and lots of animals here
也有很多大量的动物在这里
Then this is an animal paradise
那这个是一个动物的乐园
Humans are also a paradise
人类也是个乐园
Why
为什么
it has a large number of animals
它有大量的动物
let it go hunting
让它去狩猎
it has a lot of rich food
它有很多的丰富的食物
can live here
可以在这里生活
And the south is better than the north
而且南方比北方呢
It should be warmer
应该还是比较温暖的
So it was a time
所以这是一个当时的
Now the Penghu Trench
现在是澎湖海沟
But it's a very treacherous trench
但是是一个非常险恶的海沟
But 10,000 to 20,000 years ago
但是在一两万年以前
This is an animal paradise
这边是一个动物的乐园
a paradise for human beings
是人类的一个乐园
This is a
这是一个
I'll talk about it later
下面我再谈一谈
This is the world of eight-star power
就是这个八星动力的乾坤
If you take a car from Hualien to Taitung
周围假如坐车从花蓮往台东走
Hualien to Taitung
花蓮往台东走
Or go north from Taitung
或者从台东往北走
you drive a car
你开一个车
the east coast is very beautiful
东海岸非常漂亮
Surrounded by mountains and waters
周围看山光水色
Green mountains and green waters
青山绿水
very beautiful
非常的漂亮
to the middle point
到中间点的地方
you will see Eight Star Cave
就会看到八星洞
Looking around the Eight Star Cave
周围看八星洞
The scenery of Baxing Cave is very beautiful
八星洞风光非常漂亮
It is also the middle point between north and south
它也是南来北往中间点
so many tourists come here
所以很多游客来这里
you can take a rest
就可以来做休息
This is Eight Star Cave
这是八星洞
This area is a small hill
这个地区这是一个小山丘
Then the road goes down the hill
然后公路沿着山下走过去
If you look closely, on this hill
如果看细看 在这个山丘上面
many holes
有很多的洞
at least near the edge of the fog
至少在靠近雾边的地方
There are several big holes
就有好几个很大的洞
This hole is very meaningful in terms of geology
这个洞在地质学上面是非常有意义的
why
为什么呢
Because the formation of this hole is the so-called wave crashing rocks.
因为这个洞的形成是所谓海浪冲石而形成的
Well, of course, if you look at the beach here now
那么当然如果看现在海边的这里
How did you hit the stone?
怎么冲石到呢
Actually in ancient times
其实在古代
especially long ago
在这特别是非常久远的以前
ten thousand years ago
即万年以前
These holes are actually in contact with seawater.
那这些洞其实都是在和海水是接触的
So it means that the seawater probably started after the update ceremony ended
所以代表这个海水大概从那个更新式结束之后
slowly go up
慢慢的往上升
And what about this land?
然后这个陆地呢
The land on the east coast will also continue to rise
东海岸的陆地也是会一直往上升
because of what
因为什么
This happens to be on the Eurasian plate
这刚好是在这个欧亚板块
And around here on the Philippine plate
还有菲律宾板块的这个附近
So what about the movement of this plate?
所以这个板块的运动呢
It also contributed to the improvement of the land trade here.
也促使了这一个这边地贸往上提升
That is to say, when the rate of increase and the rate of sea level rise
那所以说当这个提升的速度和海水面升的速度
What happens after the two reach a state of equilibrium?
两个达到一个平衡状态之后呢
The waves are constantly crashing against this
海浪就不断的在冲这个这个严避
So these caves form a lot of sea rock caves
所以这些洞穴就形成很多海石的洞穴
so there are many caves
所以上面有很多的洞穴
So this cave is certainly formed by some natural factors
所以这个洞穴固然是一些自然因素所形成的
But then it became a dwelling place for humans
但是后来也就变成了人类的一个居所
Ancient humans found this good
古代人类发现这个很好
There is such a hole inside the natural
有这么一个洞里面天然的
Can take shelter from the wind
可以避风
Such a place where you can avoid the ocean
可以避洋的这样一个场所
So it becomes an archaeological site
所以就变成了一个考古的遗址
so humans live here
所以人类在这里居住
So there's a lot left over from his life
所以就下来很多他的生活的遗留
So thus it becomes a ruin
所以因此就变成了一个遗址
So thus it becomes now a
所以因此就变成了现在变成了一个
Because it is a very important site of the country
因为这是国家很重要的一个遗址
That's why it's called a national monument
所以叫做国定遗址
At the same time, the Management Office of the East Coast National Scenic Office of the Ministry of Communications
同时交通部东海岸国家风景处管理处
It is also listed as a National Specific Scenic Area
也把它列为国家特定风景区
means it has its importance
代表它有它的重要性
importance
重要性
There is also a so-called Baxiandong Visitor Center here.
这边还有设立一个所谓八线洞游客中心
If you go to the east coast to play
诸位假如到东海岸玩
I strongly recommend
我是强烈建议
everyone can stop here
大家可以在这边停留一下
the scenery is very beautiful
風光是非常漂亮
I think the scenery of our Taiwan
我覺得我們台灣的風景
Especially the scenery of East Korea
特別東韓的風景
That is, we don't have to travel abroad
就是我們不用出國去旅遊
Actually it's good here
其實這邊就很好
If you can stay here for a few days
這邊就能讓你去住幾天的話
you must be a star
你一定是星曠神移
favorite
寵如皆旺
this is a very nice place
這個非常好的一個地方
This is very but a pity
這個很但很可惜的
such a nice place
這麼好的一個地方
but none of us know
但是我們沒有人知道
Nobody knows
沒有人知道
Watch carefully
注意看
Now since Luke opened
現在自從路客開放之後
look here
注意看這邊
There is a car here every day
每天的這邊有輛車
Dozens of cars are parked on the side of the road
幾十輛有輛車都停在路邊
what is he doing
他停在目的幹什麼
has two purposes
有兩個目的
There is a visitor center here
這邊有一個遊客中心
To the restroom
上廁所
So many people have to go to the toilet
這麼多人都要去上廁所
so that toilet is kept clean
所以那廁所保持得很乾淨
also keep cleaning
也不斷的要打掃
because there are too many people
因為人太多了
the second
第二個
There is a temple just by the road
剛好路邊有一個廟
Lingyan Temple
叫林顏寺
go in and have a look
進去看一看
Burning Township
燒住鄉
This is the Eight Immortals Cave
這個就到八仙洞
then left
然後就走了
or there is a restaurant here
或者這邊還有一個飯館
then have a lunch
然後吃一頓午餐
then left
然後就走了
So tens of thousands of people
所以每天有幾萬人的
this tourist comes here
這個遊客來這裡
But I believe almost no one knows
但是我相信幾乎沒有人知道
This turned out to be a very important archaeological site
這竟然是一個非常重要的一個考古遺址
And it's a national monument
而且是一個國定的遺址
so it's a pity
所以是一個非常可惜的
So where is the important line from this site?
那麼這個遺址到重要線在哪裡呢
This was in the 57th year of the Republic of China
這個是在民國57年的時候
Professor Song Wenxun of National Taiwan University
台灣大學的宋文勳 宋教授
So he found the culture of the old times over there
那麼他在那邊發現了舊時期時代的文化
He named it Changbing Culture
他當時就命名為長兵文化
This is the senior who was guided by our Shi Yu at that time
這個是當時我們石瑜所導前輩
Changbing Culture named by Mr. Li Ji
李紀先生所命名的長兵文化
So Professor Song did excavations here
那麼宋教授在這裡做了發掘
Excavations dug up these so-called old times
發掘挖出來了這些有所謂的舊時期
That was the first time in Taiwan to discover the culture of the old era
那是在台灣第一次發現到舊時期時代的文化
Well, at that time, he also made some age determinations.
那麼當時他也去做了一些年代的一些測定
Then he discovered that in this era
那麼他發現當時的這個年代
Looking at it from here, it is about 5,000 years old
作為看這邊大概是五千多年
About 5300 years, 5400 years
大概是五千三百年 五千四百年
So this is probably about 5,000 years ago
那麼這個大概都是在五千年左右
Only one age is above the tallest cave
只有一个年代在最高的一个洞穴上面
a year unearthed
所出土的一个年代
It is called greater than 15,000 years
它是叫做大于15000年
but it doesn't know how many years
但它不知道几年
The result is that
出来的结果就是说
Possibly greater than 15,000 years old
可能大于超过15000年
more than 15000
超过15000
but how many years
但到底多少年代
Because of the limited technology at that time
因为限于当时的策定的技术
So it has no way to understand
所以它还没有办法去理解到
so this becomes one big one puzzle
所以这变成一个大的一个谜题
How old is this White Star Cave?
到底这个白星洞它的年代是多少
According to reason, it is the era of the era
照道理就时期时代的年代
Should be at least 10,000 years old
应该至少超过1万年
Why is it only 5,000 years old
为什么的年代会只有5000多年
And here it is 15000
而这边到底是15000
how much is it
到底是多少呢
How many thousands of years?
到底几万年呢
so no one knows
所以谁也不知道
But after the discovery of Nagahama's English culture
但是长濱英文化的发现之后
But it has become one of our Taiwan's history
却变成我们台湾历史上的一个
very important one
很重要的一张
Take a look at our elementary school textbooks
作为看看我们的国小的课本
middle school textbooks
国中的课本
Its first one talks about the culture of the period
它的第一张上面讲就时期文化
Must talk about Nagahama
一定要讲到长濱
Nagahama English culture
要长濱英文化
But many students ask
但是很多学生就问了
After all, you are not talking about the culture of the period
到底结果你不是讲就时期文化
would it have been 10,000 years ago
它会在1万年以前吗
Why is this place more than 5,000 years old?
为什么这边年代5000多年呢
So in the end this 15,000 years is just greater than
那到底这个15000年只是大于
How long have you been looking for it?
到底找的多久呢
so no one knows
所以谁也不知道
So it becomes a question mark
所以变成一个question mark
a question
一个疑问
what about this thing
那么这个东西呢
so until a few years ago
所以一直到几年以前
The Ministry of Culture is looking for us
这个文化部就找我们
Hope to do some further research
希望能够进一步地去做一些研究
investigate to understand
调查去理解
Because after the 57th year of the Republic of China, Professor Song
因为从宋教授民国57年以后
no one does research anymore
再没有人做研究了
No one has done research for decades
好几十年都没有人做研究
But the question is still hanging there
但是这个问题还一直悬在那里
still need to solve
还需要去做解决
At that time, Professor Song
那当时宋教授
He also made some inductions on Changmin culture
他也对长民文化做了一些归纳
he said first
他说第一个
He said at that time
他说当时呢
There was no farming phenomenon at that time
当时没有农叙的现象
At that time, no one was found at this time
就当时没有发现到这个时候的人
he can recrop
他可以重作物
no agricultural phenomenon
没有农业的现象
the second
第二个
these people
这个这些人里面
he won't grind period
他不会磨织时期
to be naughty
去淘气
Those things are in line with
那这些东西都是符合
A basic definition of the so-called old culture
所谓旧时期文化的一个基本定义
Another third is
另外第三个是
Times are all tricks to beat waves
时期都是打波法之招
no grinding period
都没有磨的时期
It's time to make
都是打制的时期
then in addition
那么另外
It belongs to the entire eastern part of Asia
它是属于整个亚洲东部的
as well as the southern tradition called kanfa
以及南部的叫做看伐气传统
Therefore, cutting gas represents a period
所以看伐气是代表一种时期
The kind of felling gas used to chop things
用来砍东西的那种砍伐气的
an industrial tradition
一种工业的传统
So it made an induction on the time
所以它对当时做了一个归纳
This induction is basically correct
这个归纳基本上是没有错
But they all lack some more detailed understanding
但是都缺乏一些比较详细的一些理解
This was also guessed by Professor Song at the time.
这个是当时宋教授也推测了
Where did Taiwan's product culture come from?
这个到底台湾的产品文化从哪里来的
So he also made some guesses
所以他也做了一些推测
So it may still come from most of the South Seas
所以可能还是来自于大多南洋海
In this region of the South China Sea
多南洋海的这个区域里面
So the discovery of this product culture
所以这个产品文化的发现
It is very important to the history of Taiwan
对台湾的历史是非常重要
It is also Taiwan that can push Taiwan's history forward
也是台湾能够把台湾历史往前推到
earlier time
更早的时间
But many issues still need to be understood
但是很多问题都还需要去理解
to solve
去解决
Especially to understand the human beings of the old times
特别是了解旧时期时代的人类
then we need more of this information
那么我们还需要更多的这些资料
So therefore I personally probably just
所以因此我个人大概是刚刚
It also introduces about from 1997 of the Republic of China
也介紹了大概從民國97年
We also accept this document will
我們也接受了這個文件會
Now the Ministry of Culture and Taichung publicity entrust
現在文化部以及台中宣傳委託
We also implement a further step to do this
我們也執行進一步地去做這個
The Eight Immortals Cave who joined the army
參兵的這個八仙洞的
This research that has been investigating
一直的調查的這個研究
we hope to understand
我們希望可以了解
Of course, we also set a lot of agenda
那當然我們也設定了很多的議題
to understand further
要進一步地去理解
to learn about
去去了解
Then this is that we will do it more systematically than before
那這個是我們會比當時做更有系統
It is our whole team and the process of work
是我們整個團隊以及工作的流程
Work has a SOP process
工作有一個SOP流程
We do scientific research
我們去做很有科學性的來做研究
do research
做調查
then this is
那這個是
Then we this after a few years
然後我們這個經過幾年
The most important first is that we're going to discover new holes
最重要第一個是我們要去發現新的洞
why now
為什麼現在過去
This was the era of Professor Song Wenxun
這是當時在宋文勳教授的時代
the cave he made
這個他所當時所做的洞穴
his own cave
他就自己的洞穴
Regrettably
很遺憾的
when the work is done
當工作做完之後
what has become of this cave
這個洞穴就變成什麼了
into a ready-made temple
變成一個很現成的廟宇
A lot of
很多的
After you dug the hole there was a hole there
你把洞挖出来之后空了一个洞在那里
It's just right to go in and set up a few lanes
它刚刚好进去摆几个巷岸
put a few buddhas
摆几个佛
After the diary has an appointment, it becomes an altar
日记约了以后就变成一个神坛
a temple language
一个庙语
So almost all the holes above are occupied by these temple words
所以上面就几乎大家所有的洞都被这些庙语所占据了
Then it will do temple language
然后它要做庙语
while doing some construction inside
当里面做一些建设
to dig out the soil
要把土挖掉
Then put some altars
然后要摆一些神坛
So the chair was destroyed again.
所以又把这个椅子也就破坏掉了
Below is broken even if possible
下面即使有可能也都破坏了
Therefore, there is probably no way to do further research on these hole sequences.
所以这些洞序大概是没有办法再进一步的去做研究了
So it is necessary to find a new hole sequence
所以就必须要去找寻新的洞序
our part
我们这个部分
So we have to do a survey
所以我们要必须要做一个调查
so you pay attention
所以你注意看
This is our new survey in recent years
这是我们这几年我们新做调查
Therefore, quite a few new hole sequences have been discovered.
所以新发现了相当多的洞序
this is quite difficult work
这个是相当困难的工作
Because these holes are not there waiting for you to discover
因为这些洞序它不是摆在那里等你去发现
In fact, you all know that landslides
其实诸位知道土石流
right
对不对
landslides
土石流没上
Especially typhoons on the east coast
尤其东海岸的台风
There are many landslides
有很多没是土石流
Just cover all the caves
就把所有的洞穴都已經覆蓋住了
are full
都已經蓋滿了
so can't see at all
所以根本看不見了
so we're going to find the cave
所以我們要把洞穴找出來
Especially thick straight batches
尤其又覆蓋得很厚的直批
plant covered
植物覆蓋的
So it's very difficult to keep working
所以要繼續做工作非常困難的
especially in many places
尤其很多地方都是
because it is a wall
因為它是一個竅壁
So it's pretty dangerous to work
所以工作起來相當危險
like here
像這邊
These are very steep walls
這都是很陡的竅壁
look for a group of caves
上面要找一群洞穴
But our team members
但是我們的團隊人員
It's all very risky
都是很冒險氾濫
adventure flood
冒險氾濫
So go in and look slowly
所以進去都慢慢找
through some expert methods
透過一些專探的方法
through some means
透過一些手段
Then put the caves one by one
然後把洞穴一個一個的
can find out
都能夠去找出來
So you can't see part of the cave at all
所以完全看不見洞穴的部分
go find the cave again
去把洞穴再去找出來
So now it becomes so many caves
所以現在就變成這麼多的洞穴
So this means
所以這代表
At that time the area
當時這個地區
when it was formed in the sea stone cave
它在海石洞形成的時候
Actually formed a lot of caves
其實形成了非常多的洞穴
at different times
在不同時間
because as the crust rises
因為隨著地殼的上升
so it slowly
所以它這個慢慢的
highly eroded
高度的来侵蚀
like the earliest ones are relatively high range
像最早的是比较高的范围
Then when the Disk rises
然后当这个Disk上升之后
There is also a range of lower erosion
还有侵蚀比较低的范围
Then Disk goes up again
然后Disk再上升
and erosion further down
还有侵蚀再下面
so the higher the cave
所以越高的洞穴
it should be earlier
它年代应该是越早
then the lower cave
然后越低的洞穴
it will be later
它年代会越晚
then this is
那这个是
You are big enough to see the tallest cave above
你足以看上面这个最高洞穴
probably here
大概是这里
Currently found to be about 200 meters high
目前发现大概200公尺的高度
about 30 meters down there
那下面大概30公尺
30 meters
30公尺
represent different times
是代表不同的时间
The caves formed by these
所形成的这些的洞穴
this is
这个是
after we found out
我们发现之后
Kangjia Skills of Science and Ancient Science
科古学的康家本领
Excavation after investigation
调查之后就做发掘
why
为什么呢
you from the bunker
你从地堡
Information available to you
你可以获得的资料
is limited after all
毕竟是有限的
you have to dig under it
你必须要从它地底下去挖
Because the artifacts of ancient humans
因为古代人类的文物
slowly with time
慢慢都会随着时间
buried under the ground
被淹埋在地底下了
So you have to go through a scientific
所以你必须要透过一个科学的
a systematic approach
一个由系统的方法
dig your stuff out
把你的东西挖掘出来
and then be able to do some research
然后才能够去做一些研究
Then these are the ones we choose
然后这些就是我们所选择的
some caves of different heights
一些不同的高度的洞穴
to carry out
来进行
to dig
挖掘
Digs represent different times
挖掘代表不同的时间
The connotations in also represent different eras
中的内涵也代表不同的时代
So we work like this
因此我们这样工作
This is our different choice of blood
这个是我们不同的动血选择
different heights for digging
做发掘的不同的高度
from the actual meter
从实际公尺
The last track is close to the height of 200 meters
最后一道接近200公尺的高度
Excavation actions are carried out in different blood movements
不同的动血里面来进行发掘的动作
This is what we're digging
这个是我们在发掘的
Very hard
非常辛苦
inside this move
这个动里面
Under the ground after punching in
打进去之后在地底下
Often can reach seven or eight meters
往往可以到七八公尺
very deep
非常深
especially in summer
尤其在夏天的时候
It's airtight inside
又密不通风在里面
So our staff worked very, very hard
所以我们工作人员非常非常辛苦
and very dangerous
而且非常危险
why
为什么呢
On top of the hole there will continue to come down
在洞上面会不断有落实下来
Because the above will continue to implement
因为上面不断的会落实
so what do our workmates bring
所以我们的工作同学带什么
with helmet
带钢盔 带安全帽
Come on, why is the hat being implemented and smashed like this
来为什么带帽被落实砸到这样子
this is a very
这个是一个非常
but very important
但是非常重要
So in this
所以在这个里面
You can find many of these things in it
从里面可以发现到这些很多这些东西
As an ordinary person but do not know
作为看一般人却不认识
say it's all stone
来说这都是石头
We often have many people ask us tourists
我们常常很多人问我们游客
what is this
这什么东西
He said no
他说没有啊
We see a lot of seaside
我们海边看好多啊
Nice by the sea
海边的不错
These stones are from the sea
这些石头都是来自于海边
Humans at that time picked these stones from the sea
当时的人类在海边来选取了这些的石头
They choose stones purposefully
他们有目的去选取石头
Then the stone itself is processed to make its stone tools
然后这个石头本身加工来做成它的石器
So you can see this is
所以可以看看这个是
What I just said is that I will get angry
这个刚讲的就是会砍发气
it uses these pebbles from the sea
它使用海边的这些鹅卵石
Then come here after the wave
然后在这边来经过打波之后
knock down the flakes
把石片打下来
Then there are some seals here
然后这边产生了一些封印
These seals can have the function of cutting
这些封印可以具有切割的功能
or cut hair function
或者砍发的功能
So probably in the past these humans
所以大概在过去的这些人类
It's actually not like copper and iron now
它其实不像现在有铜器有铁器
It's exactly when it needs to work
它完全就是它需要工作的时候
Go to the beach and cut these pebbles and come back
再到海边去剪了这些鹅卵石回来
and then to process
然后就来加工
then do it
然后来做
We also did a lot of experiments
我们也做了很多实验
How did this human do it?
到底这个人类怎么做出来的
We went to get the stone ourselves
我们自己也去拿了石头
Knock, knock, wow, I can't knock on that one, my hands are numb
敲敲看 哇 那個是敲不動 手都麻了
He couldn't knock a piece down. It was very difficult.
他敲不下了一片下來 非常困難
very difficult with this stone
非常困難 用這個石頭的
very hard
非常地堅硬 按三言的石頭
Basalt stone is very hard
玄武岩的石頭 非常地堅硬
It's very, very difficult for you to knock it down
你要去敲下來就很非常困難
My hands are so skinny I can't knock them off
手都破皮了 都敲不下來
Later we experimented with various methods
後來我們有實驗各種方法
Later found a fastest way
後來發現一個最快的方法
These people just need to drop on the ground
這些人只要放在地上一摔
he actually cracked
他實際上就崩開了
and he cracked beautifully
而且他很漂亮地崩開
Then do local processing on top
然後才上面再做局部的加工
Then these methods will be formed
然後就會形成了這些方式
That's why we call it the Wrestling Method
所以我們這個叫摔疾法
may have produced such a
可能產生了這樣一個
This is what we found through our experiments
這也是我們透過我們實驗分析出來的
such a result
這樣一種結果
Learn about the technology of human beings making stone tools at that time
了解到當時人類製造石器的技術是怎麼樣
Also we are inside this hole
另外我們在這個洞裡面
have been excavated very carefully.
都經過了非常仔細的這些發掘
We did it to see that there is a firepit here
我們做的看這邊有火塘
The location of each of these stone tools
這些每一個石器分布的位置
This means that human beings in this cave at that time
這代表當時人類在這個洞
just forming
剛剛在形成的
It went in when it just came out of the water
刚刚才离开水面的时候它就进去了
so we'll find a lot of pebbles inside
所以我们在里面会发现很多鹅卵石
In addition, they use these pebbles to make stone tools
另外他们就利用这些鹅卵石就制造石器
then inside it maybe when hunting
然后在里面它也许当时狩猎
There is barbecue grilled food
有烤肉 烤食物
So there's a lot of these fire sugar in the hole
所以就有很多的这些火糖在洞里面
So fire sugar make fire sugar A fire sugar B
所以火糖做一下火糖A 火糖B
That is to say, the fire sugar is the place where the fire is burned.
就是说火糖就是烧火的地方
So here we can find traces of the fire at that time
所以这边可以发现到当时烧火的痕迹
So on behalf of the human beings at that time
所以代表当时的人类
This so-called time like Mao drinking blood
这个所谓如茅饮血的时候
They make stone tools in the cave
他们在洞里面制造石器
cook food in it
在里面烧火煮食物
The event of its whole life is its cave
它整个生活的事件就是它这个洞穴
then in this hole
那么在这个洞里面
Also found some of this
也发现了有一些这个
what does this look like
这个作为看着什么
just naughty
就是淘气
The one in front of it is completely irrelevant
它前面那个完全是风马牛不相及的
This is the human race of the New Era, about 3,000 years old.
这个是年代大概三千年的新时期时代的人类
It means that human beings tens of thousands of years ago
就代表说在这个几万年前的人类
thousands of years of human beings
还有几千年的人类
it will use animals
它都会利用动物的
come as a residence
来作为居住
So humans in the past served as nest dwellers
所以过去的人类作为巢居
so tree dwelling
所以树居巢居
and cave dwellers
和洞穴居
is to use different terrain
就是利用不同的地形
living place
来做生活的居住场所
we did too
我们也做了
The chronological analysis just mentioned
刚刚讲过的年代学的分析
Well now we do quite a bit of this
那么现在我们做了相当多的这些
In the past in the era of Professor Song Wenxun
过去在宋文勋教授的时代
Due to technical limitations
由于限于技术
How many years did he do it
他是做几个年代出来
and the age of doubt
而且有疑问的年代
we pass these
我们透过这些
Our new technological approach
我们现在新的科技方法
we can do a lot
我们可以做很多
Now there are seventies and eighties
现在有七八十个年代
so its overall channel is very high
所以它的整个信路非常高
from the current age
从现在目前的年代
The earliest we can reach 30,000 years
最早我们可以到达三万年
Can reach 30,000 years of data
可以到达三万年的数据
Watch carefully
注意看
this is all we have
这个是我们所有的
Pay attention to our data
注意看我们的这些数据
line up
排列起来
The earliest age here is 30,000 years old
这边最早的年代到三万年
and then sorted all the way down
然后一直排列下来排列
Generate a GAP here
到这边产生一个GAP
Down from about 5,000 years ago
下来大概从五千年开始
down again
又下来
like until now
像一直到现在
Well, what is very beautiful about this age is the data of this age
那么这个年代非常漂亮的是这个年代数据
here is very meaningful
这边是非常有意义
I won't talk about it here because it's another academic question.
我这边就不讲 因为这是另外一个学术问题
In fact, this age is probably the earliest at the current location
事实上说 这个年代大概最早目前的为止
At the current height, the age is about 30,000 years
以目前的高度 年代大概就三万年
Now tell me what I've said so far
那现在告诉我 目前的为止的话
Humans of our Changmin culture, the age of the eight stars
我们长民文化 八星那种年代人类
about 30,000 years ago
大概可以到三万年前
So the humans here are probably the earliest
所以这边的人类大概就是年代最早
up to 30,000 years
可以到三万年
These are the results obtained so far
这是目前所获得的这些结果
In addition, we are also concerned about the accumulation of strata in this cave
另外我们也对这个洞穴里的地层的堆积
Some made this Poxi in great detail
有的做了非常详细的这个潑溪
As a matter of fact this is a cave and these accumulations of this formation
做为看这是一个洞穴这个地层的这些堆积
this is very interesting
这个非常有意思
From the heap we don't just learn that it's a natural process
从堆积里面我们不只是了解到它一个自然的程序
Because the cave itself its original
因为洞穴本身它原来的
here are big pebbles
这有大的鹅卵石
This represents when the cave was formed
这代表当时洞穴形成的时候
Pebbles from the sea will rush into the hole
海边的鹅卵石会冲进洞里面去
Then slowly began to deposit on the top
然后上面慢慢开始产生了沉积
This deposit may have flowed in from outside the cave.
这个沉积也许是从洞外水流进去的
these grades
這些成績
then to the top
然後到上面以後
Come back and find that the score is oblique
再過來就發現這個成績是斜的
top is flat
上面是平的
Why? Because it's late in the month
為什麼呢?因為到了這個月晚的時候
maybe a natural disaster
也許有自然的災害
earthquake
地震
So the hole is blocked
所以這個洞就被堵住了
After blocking
堵住以後
This grade outside
外面的這個成績物
Only through some very small forces
只能透過一些非常小的力量
Or the force of the water rushing into the hole
或者水沖的力量進入在洞裡面去
We found that around 3000 years
我們發現大概在3000年左右
probably all the holes
大概所有的洞
basically blocked
基本上都被封住了
this thing is very
這個東西就非常
let's analyze the soil
我們去分析這土壤
analyze the rock
分析這岩石
we can learn
我們可以了解到
A change in the natural environment reflected at that time
當時反映出來的一個自然環境的變遷
and natural disasters
以及在自然的災害
Especially in Baxian East area
尤其在八弦東地區
Until now
到現在為止
there are many disasters
還有很多災害
rockfall anytime
隨時有落石
collapse at any time
隨時有崩塌
so this disaster
所以這個災害
Since ancient times, only
從古到今都只有了
So this also reflects
所以這也反映出來
Humans at that time
當時人類
Especially we found in the stratum
尤其我們在地層裡面發現
people come and go
人類是來來去去的
come and go
來了以後就走了
came again after leaving
走了以後又來了
That this and the natural environment
那這個和自然的環境
and natural disasters are basically closely related
以及自然災害人基本上是有密切的關係的
Then of course we also want this
那麼這個另外當然我們也去想要
These data also help us to understand
這些資料也幫助我們去了解到
Where did these humans come from?
那這些人類到底從哪裡來的
In the past, Professor Song Wenxun speculated that it might have come from South China
過去宋文勳教授推測可能是來自於華南
In this regard, we basically do not deny him.
那這方面我們基本上面也並不去否認他
But we also considered his possible ties to the south
但是我們也考慮到他可能和南方的關係
relationship with the Philippines
和菲律賓之間的關係
There are many problems
這中間有很多的問題
We still need to go further to do some discussions
我們還需要去進一步的去去做一些討論
The other is our past geology
那另外就是我們過去地質學界
I have always wanted to know the address on the east coast of Taiwan
一直想要了解到台灣東海岸的地址
The rate of crustal rise is the fastest in the world
地殼上升速度是全世界最快的
very fast rise every year
每年上升速度非常快的
We can also take advantage of the heights of the different caves in the Eight Immortals Cave
我們也可以利用八仙洞的不同洞穴的高度
have the exact age
有確切的年代
Let's estimate the address on the east coast
我們來推估東海岸的地址上面的
What is the rate at which the ground rises?
地層上升的速率是怎麼樣
So it's because each of our caves is to me
所以這因為我們每個洞穴就對我年代
and then its higher level
然後又有它的高層
It can be inferred from this aspect
從這個方面可以推算
rate of increase per year
當時可能每一年上升的速率
Looks like every year from now
從現在看起來大概每一年
Probably the time when the East China Sea rose was about 7
大概東海上升的年代大概在7
Up to 10 mm is quite a fast speed.
到10个m m是相当快的一个速度啊
So some of us speculate that this is after the customs year
所以我们有人推测这个在过入关年之后呢
Taitung's Green Island Blue Rain will slowly approach the East China Sea
台东的绿岛蓝雨会慢慢靠近到东海来啊
because he's been sliding
因为他地层一直在在滑动
I'm improving
在在提升啊
So this is the 88 first move
那么这个是这个88先动呢
In fact, since about 30,000 years ago
其实大概从三万年以来呢
Humans live there
人类就在那边居住在啊
then he will come and go
那他会来来来去去
It lasted until about 15,000 years ago.
大概一直延续到到15000年啊
Finally another group of people came in again
最后来了另外一批人再进来
Then after 3000
然后到3000年以后呢
there is another group of people
有另外一批人
So these studies can help us understand
所以这些研究呢可以帮助我们去了解到
what about the cave area
这个洞穴地区呢
The life of these human beings
这些人类的这些生活的样貌
And some changes in his culture
以及他有文化的一些变迁啊
This is our guess
这个是这是我们推测啊
Some states of human life at that time
当时人类的一个生活的一些状态啊
Then let's talk about another topic
那么下面我们再再谈一个课题
This is the farmer who came across the sea
就是这个跨海来的农民
Well, this was just mentioned earlier
那么这个刚刚前面讲过了
So while we're talking about Conanco
那么在我们在谈谈科南科
As the one I saw, this dog
作为看的这一个这个狗啊
what is this
这是这是什么
It's a dog, isn't it?
这是一条狗对不对
It's so cute as a dog.
作为看的狗啊非常可爱啊
sleep here
在这睡觉啊
we are normal now
我们现在一般的
if dead
如果死掉了
Of course our times are different now
当然我们现在时代不一样了
now your pet
现在你的宠物
if passed away
如果过世了
if after death
如果死了以后
not only to bury it properly
不但要好好地焉埋起来
cremate it
剩而要把它火化
to put in the tower
要放在塔里面去
to confess
要供起来
someone wants to put it in the house
有人要放在家里面
treat it like a baby
把它当宝贝
in ancient times
在古代的时候
I usually imagine
我一般想象
This dog is dead
这个狗死了就死了
throw it outside
把丢到外面去
eat yourself and leave it alone
把自己吃不管它
But in our Tainan Science Park
可是在我们台南科学园区
5000 years of farmers
5000年的农民
look at his dog treat like this
看一看他的狗这样对待
he did a very good job of burying him
他把他做得非常好的掩埋
So after the dog died
所以狗死掉之后
so look what he's doing really well
所以看他做得非常好的
bury it
把它掩埋起来
not a dog
并不是一条狗
There are many dogs like this
有好多条狗都是这样子的
So this means
所以这代表说
One between man and dog
当时人和狗之间的一个
very close relationship
非常亲密的这种关系
This is what we have found in Taiwan so far
这是我们台湾目前所发现
The earliest dog bred by humans
人类加养的最早的一条狗
We call it Taiwan's No. 1 Dog
我们叫台湾第一狗
Ha ha
哈哈
This Taiwanese native dog is the first dog in Taiwan
这台湾土狗在台湾第一狗
We also found it here
我们这边也发现到了
this rice just said
这稻米刚刚讲过了
This is the first rice in Taiwan
这是台湾的第一粒稻米
The earliest rice found in Taiwan
台湾目前发现最早的稻米
5000 years
5000年
Of course, this era is still later than other regions.
当然这个年代比起别的地区还是要晚
Like the current era of rice in mainland China
像中国大陆现在稻米的年代
up to 20,000 years
可以到2万年
By 19,000 years to 20,000 years
到19000多年到2万年
We have now found the earliest rice in Taiwan
我们台湾现在目前发现最早稻米
or until 5000
还是到5000年
Then this millet
那么这个小米
This is the first discovery in Taiwan
这也是台湾第一次的发现
We know that the aborigines of Taiwan have so far
我们知道台湾的原住民现在为止
Millet is a very important crop
小米是一个很重要的一个作物
Therefore, we must use millet in the new year
所以在封年纪都要用小米
Then use millet to make wine
然后用小米做酒
but where did this millet come from
但是这小米从哪里来的
when did millet start
什么时候开始有小米
never knew
过去一直都不知道
Now through our archaeological discoveries
现在我们透过我们的考古发现
Also found a lot of millet
也发现大量的小米
This millet does not come by accident
这个小米它不是偶尔来的
Or snatched from the sea
或者是在海上面抢来的
or how
或者怎么样
it's a lot
它量非常多
And the millet is all burnt
而且这小米都是被烧过的
The representative said that the amount was very large
代表说当时的量非常大
it may burn it when lether
它也许当勒瑟把它烧一烧
Just as Lesser's positive attitude towards Fang
就当勒瑟对放的积极
So the representative said that when
所以这个代表说当时
this amount is quite large
这个数量是相当大的
Not that it takes money to buy very precious
并不是说需要钱买来非常珍贵的
So the rep said
所以代表说
At that time, a multi-functional representative of human beings
当时代表人类的一个众职的
So on behalf of the agriculture at that time
所以代表当时的农业
it grows rice on the one hand
它一方面种稻米
grow millet on the one hand
一方面种小米
Of course there is a problem
当然这中间有问题
Because millet grows in a more temperate region
因为小米它生长在一个比较温带的地区
The subtropical zone in our southern Taiwan
我们台湾南部的亚热带
upper tropics
上而热带的地区
How can millet be produced
怎么会产生小米
This part is of course also a question
这个部分当然也是一个疑问
But we also know that climate change
但是我们也了解到气候的改变
Today's climate may not have been the same in the past
现在的气候过去未必是一样的
And the environment in which they were planted was not necessarily the same.
而且当时种植的环境也未必是一样的
so it is still possible to grow millet
所以仍然可以种小米
Now in the tribes of the aborigines in eastern Taiwan
现在台湾东部的原住民的部落里面
There are many kinds of rice
还有很多种小米的
There are two ruins in the area of ​​Taiwan Academy of Sciences
这个是在台湾科学院区有两个遗址
one is what we call
一个是我们叫做
This is a Nanguanli
这边是一个南关里
Nanguan Lidong Ruins
南关里东遗址
These are the two oldest ruins
这是两个年代最久的遗址
Just five thousand years
就五千年
It unearthed our first dog in Taiwan
它出土了我们台湾第一狗
Also produced Taiwan's first grain of rice
也出了台湾第一粒米
Taiwan's first millet
台湾第一粒的小米
This is when we are working
这是我们在工作的时候的
as look have very hard
作为看有非常辛苦
This has a large area of ​​excavation
这有很大面积的发掘
Then these peasants of this culture
那么这个文化的这些农民
it all comes from
它都是来自于
are from
都是来自于
are from mainland
都是來自於大陸的
Probably the coast of Guangdong
大概是廣東的沿岸
They are all the generation of the Pearl River Delta
都是珠江三角洲這一代
because of the culture there
因為那邊的文化
These cultures are very similar
這些文化是非常的類似
The representative said that these human beings
代表說這些人類
Probably from the Guangdong Delta
可能是來自於廣東三角洲
even further south
甚而更往南邊一點
One North to Hainan Island
到海南島的一北
this coastal generation
這海岸一代
probably all these people
大概都是這些人
probably his original hometown
可能是他原來的家鄉
or these people cross the sea
或者這些人跨過海
came to these Taiwan
就來到了這些台灣
this is
這個是
As a look at his technologies at that time
作為看他的這些當時的技術
has made great progress
已經非常的進步
very nice these naughty
非常漂亮的這些淘氣
Very beautiful these stone tools
非常漂亮的這些石器
These stone tools are very delicate as a model
作為看模特非常精緻的這些石器
And back
還有背器
These backs are used for
這些背器用來
as a knife for harvesting
當刀子用來收割
these rice crops
這些稻作
You see this has a very nice back knife
你看這個有非常漂亮的背刀
As these tools for reaping antiquities
作為收割古物的這些工具
And the counterpoint to what I just said
還有這剛剛講過的反枝
Made book cover
有製造書皮布
and these
還有這些
It is also sold
它同樣也售列
There are also some sold tools
也有一些售列的工具
that is its settlement
那是它的聚落
a very complete settlement
非常地完整的一個聚落
contains channels
包含裡面有渠道
There is a river
有河道
have a house
有房屋
with stick
有木杖
The whole is in the settlement
整個都在聚落裡面
After representing the people at that time
代表當時的人來以後
There is a very stable settlement
有一個非常穩定的聚落
it's not an oily
它不是一個油動性的
Mobility
移動性的
After it came to Taiwan from the mainland
它從大陸來到台灣之後
it chooses
它就選擇了
I just talked about the beach near the sea
剛剛講靠海邊的海邊
live here
就在這裡居住下來了
so it does farming
所以它從事農耕
to engage in fishing hunting
來從事捕魚 狩獵
then there is a very good one
然後有非常好的一個
a complete society
完整的一個社會
Social Structure
社會結構
the whole society
整個的這個社會
it for this environment
它對於這個環境
can have very good adaptation
可以有非常良好的適應
And its position
而它這個位置
Right on top of the sand dunes by the sea
剛好就在海邊的沙丘上面
so the location it lives in
所以它居住的這個位置
and the habitation of its past continents
和它過去的大陸的居住的環境
basically something like
基本上是類似的
So representing an immigrant
所以代表一個移民
go from one place to another
從一個地方到另外一個地方去
He still hopes to maintain
他仍然希望可以維持到
his original habits
他原來的生活習慣
can also live in
同時也可以居住在
similar to his living environment
和他居住的環境類似的
in this environment
這個環境裡面
So in the past on the southeast coast of the mainland
所以過去在大陸東南沿海
it lives by the sea
它是住在海邊
live in the dunes
住在沙丘
Taiwan still chooses sand dunes to live in
台灣它仍然選擇沙丘來做居住
This is it also has a cemetery
這個是它也有墓地
from its grave staff
從它的墓杖裡面
Has a very complete tomb staff
有非常完整的墓杖
have fixed customs
有固定的這些風俗習慣
The tomb staff of the people here are completely facing south.
這邊的人的墓杖完全朝南邊的
not facing north
不朝北的
So it must be a special custom
所以代表它一定特殊的一種風俗
then its source
那麼它的來源
We speculate that it may have come from the coast of Guangdong
我們推測可能是來自於廣東沿海
from the south of Fujian
從福建以南
Get this Hainan strip in the north of Hainan Island
得到海南島北的這個海南地帶
this is its old home
這是它的老家
such a source
這樣一個源流
In fact, it’s not just that we are in Taiwan
其實不只說我們在台灣
to the whole world
對整個世界上面
also has its significance
也有它重要的意義
why
為什麼呢
Because now we are talking about the origin of the so-called Austronesian people
因為現在講所謂南島民族的起源
because everyone needs to know
因為大家要知道
The Austronesian peoples are from the southeast coast of the mainland
南島民族是從大陸的東南沿海
and then migrated southward
然後一直向南邊遷徙
then to the pacific
然後到太平洋
current residence
目前所居住的
these austronesian peoples of the pacific
太平洋的這些南島民族
think a lot of it comes from
認為很多都是來自於
from the southeast coast of this continent
來自於這個大陸東南沿海
and Taiwan
和台灣這一帶
Then our discovery in Tainan Branch
那我们台南科的发现
for such a theory
对于这样一个理论
has a supporting role
就产生了一个支持的作用
Of course there are different views
当然也有不一样的看法
But now the mainstream
但是现在目前的主流
is such a mainstream
是这样一个主流
So our findings are even stronger
所以我们的发现更强顾了
such a view
这样一种看法
Of course we also did it
当然我们对它也做了
According to our own material
根据我们自己的材料
Also made a lot of corrections
也做了很多的修正
this is a
这个是一个
so we Taiwan
所以我们台湾
Its discovery is not just of significance to Taiwan
它的发现不只是台湾的意义
and has worldwide significance
而且具有世界性的意义
tell another story
下面再讲一个故事
stonemason on a desert island
叫做荒岛上的石匠
this is very interesting
这个非常有意思的
it is this
是这个
This so-called desert island
这个所谓荒岛
Refers to Qingmei Island in Penghu
是指澎湖的青梅岛
what time is it now
现在几点了
Ome Island on this deserted island
这个荒岛上的青梅岛
This island is actually for going to Ome
这个岛其实是为去过青梅
very beautiful
很漂亮
But it's a desert island
但的确是个荒岛
no one
没有什么人
And the traffic is very inconvenient
而且交通非常的不方便
We are going to Penghu
我们这到澎湖去
all of us are
大家都是
The deepest impression must be that everywhere is black
最深的印象一定是到处是黑的
black stones everywhere
到处都是黑的石头
Why
为什么
Because there are a lot of basalt rocks here
因为这边都是很多的玄武岩
The basalt is of course harming it
这玄武岩当然是害它
because it's
因为它的
due to address
地址情况而产生的
Because after the past volcanic eruptions in Penghu
因为澎湖过去的火山喷发之后
Much of its magma is transported to flow out
它的很多岩漿运往流出来之后
many so-called basalts
就形成了很多的所谓玄武岩
So you can see basalt rocks everywhere in Penghu
所以到澎湖到处都可以看到玄武岩
Well, this basalt is generally called black stone.
那么这个玄武岩我们一般叫黑石
its texture is very hard
它的质地非常坚硬
It can be divided into different categories
它又可以分成不同的类别
A so-called fine basalt
一种叫所谓细质玄武岩
The other is called subtractive basalt
另外一个叫减性玄武岩
Then the texture of this reduced basalt is relatively fine
那么这个减性玄武岩的质地比较细致
The texture of fine basalt is more airy
而细质玄武岩它的质地比较有气泡
There are often bubbles that are softer
有常有气泡比较软那样子
So these are two different
那么这就是两种不同的
This form of basalt
这个玄武岩的这种形态
Well, on Qimei's side
那么在七美这边
mostly reduced basalt
大部分都是减性玄武岩
so its texture is very hard
所以它的这个质地非常坚硬
and meticulous
而且细致
This is in Qimei area
这就是在七美地区
Then when the volcano erupted
那这些当时火山喷发的时候
After the magma flows out
这个岩漿运流出来之后
Its form will produce many
它的形态会在澎湖产生很多的
this so-called contact
这个所谓的接触
Du Zhuang's end of this phenomenon
杜壮的结底的这种现象
like this
就像这样子
as watch by the sea
作为看在海边
You can see that it looks like this when you hit the top here
可以看到这边打上面就这样子
This is how it looks when you look up close
这样一路就近看就这样子
very beautiful
非常漂亮的
This is a kind of duzhuang ending
这个是一种杜壮的一种结底
This is because after the gushing out along the river
这是因为当时沿江涌流出来以后
its special shape
它的这种特殊的形态
a special form of
所形成的一种特殊形态的
this condensation
这种凝结
This warm diarrhea it becomes a
这个温泻它就变成了一个
very important ingredient
很重要的一个食材
Then this ancient man was very smart
那么这个古代人类非常聪明
it found the stone
它就发现了这个石头
Its texture is very fine
它的质地非常的细致
very hard
非常坚硬
So he thinks this ingredient is
那么所以他就认为这个食材是
can be used as an important tool for it
可以作为它工具的一项很重要的
an ingredient
一项食材
see this as
作为看这个
then until now
那现在一直到现在为止
These Penghu residents
这些澎湖居民
Still use a lot of these ingredients
还是大量的使用这些食材
including construction
包含建筑用的
Holy Child Contains Faith Inside Temple
圣儿包含庙里面的信仰
holy children art
圣儿说艺术品
It's all a lot of just using this ingredient
都是很多只是利用这种食材
Xuanwu Garden as a look at the buildings that contain it
宣武园作为看这些包含它的建筑
The twin-heart stone household that contains Sheng Erqinmei
包含圣儿亲美的双心石户
They also use these big stones from Xuanwu Garden
也都是用这些大的宣武园的石头
piled up
堆起来的
these are works of art
这些是艺术品
Therefore, for the residents of Penghu, this Xuanwu Garden
所以这个玄武园对于澎湖的居民而言
is a very important ingredient
是一个非常重要的一个食材
It is also an important food industry
也是一个重要的一个食材产业
So we are in Ome Island
那么我们这个是在青梅岛
I did the survey in 1983
我是在1983年去做调查
We will do it when we get to Ome Island
我们到青梅岛以后就做
just like us
就像我们一样
Go everywhere to find these ancient relics
到处要去找这些古代的遗物
found a large number of these stone tools
发现有大量的这些石器
There are many stone tools
这些石器非常多
very tree very big
非常树 非常大
I was skeptical
我当时就怀疑
This stone so many stone tools
这个石头这么多的石器
Not many people live on the island
它岛上没有住几个人
why does it have
它为什么会有
so many stone tools here
这么多的石器在这里
Almost densely packed with stone tools
几乎是密密麻达的都是石器
if the population is very small
如果人口非常少
It doesn't need so many stone tools
它更不需要用那么多的石器
to make tools
来做工具
So I guessed
所以我当时就推测
this may have other meaning
这个可能有别的意义
it may be a factory
它可能是一个工厂
or as a production and marketing
或者作为一个产销的
a factory of stone tools
一个石器制造的一个工厂
So this one finally hits the year 2000
所以这个终于到了2000年
At that time, I was in the same university as the next one.
那个时候我就和下位一大学的
A Berry Rollade
一个Berry Rollade
and what we can do
还有我们地可所的
a professor's researcher
一个教授的研究员
Also retired Ye Xuewen Professor Ye
也退休了叶学文 叶教授
Let's go to Qinmei to have a look
我们一起到秦美再去看一看
take a look
看一看
Later, when we arrived at Qinmei, we discovered that
后来到秦美后来我们发现
Sure enough, I found out that my statement was confirmed.
果然发现肯定我的说法
I found several so-called large
我发现了好几个所谓大型的
The so-called period factory
所谓时期制造厂
What is period factory
什么叫时期制造厂
It was the ancient humans
就是当时古代人类
Every day in the manufacturing period
每天在制造时期
A lot of waste will be generated after the manufacturing period
制造时期以后会产生很多的废料
So pile it on the ground
所以堆在地面上面
pile up like a mountain
就像山一样的堆起来
So it becomes one we call
所以就变成一个我们叫
Besides, I pack a lot of tools of the production period inside
而且在里面包很多的制造时期的工具
So this is a period factory
所以这就是一个时期制造厂
This is our Qin Meidao
这就是我们的秦美岛
Qinmei Island is a very beautiful island
秦美岛非常漂亮的一个岛
So look at this island is the roundabout
所以看这个岛就是环岛
then on this coast
然后在这个海岸地带
There are many strong knots
有很多的助壮结理的
This kind of Xie Lianzhu who promotes the five words exists
这种宣传五言的解廉柱存在
Here become ancient humans
这边就变成古代人类
important field of its choice to real estate
它的选择来实财的重要的场域
So ancient humans were very intelligent
所以古代人类智慧非常高的
where do these people come from
这些人从哪里来的
from Taiwan
从台湾来的
So they came to Peng Hua
所以他们来到彭华
They chose a place to live
他们就选择了一个地方住下来
This place is called Nangang Ruins here
这个地方在这里叫南岗遗址
This island seems to be
这个岛好像是
It's a place where you can dig the ground and prepare for the wind.
是一个挖地 可以备风的一个地方
Because the northeast monsoon in Penghu is very strong
因为澎湖的东北季风很强
So they chose here to make a settlement
所以他们选择这里做一个聚落
gather here
聚在这里
Then the wind can block the wind
然后风可以挡风
And then a little village sits here
然后一个小村子坐在这里
What are these people doing?
这些人呢 干嘛
what is his only job
他唯一的工作是什么东西
Just after going out during the day
就白天出去以后呢
Just to this coastal area
就到这个海岸地带呢
What about these three places?
这三个地方呢
Come and find ingredients
来去找食材 打食器
tableware
打食器
So we envy them
所以我们就很羡慕他们呢
Here I live as if it expires American drama
我这边呢 住为假如到期美剧
This is Twin Star Ishido
这边就是双星石户
very beautiful
非常漂亮
the sea is very beautiful
海非常美 非常美
These people sit there every day and hit stones
这些人呢 每天坐在那边打石头
I think they play folk songs and hit rocks for a year
我想他们一年上山歌打石头
really sit every day
真的 每天就坐
But it's also boring to think about
但是也很无聊想起来
but it's very
但是这里面非常
Then there are several large
然后这边就是有好几个大型的
This stone tool factory along the coast
这个石器制造厂 沿着海岸
This is what made stone tools at that time
这就是当时制造石器的
And what about this part?
然后这一个部分呢
watch this
注意看这个
this is what we did
这个是我们做的
This help has also been excavated
这个举助一直也做了发掘
Watch carefully
注意看
At that time, I helped so I saw naughty
当时举助 所以看到淘气
This secret is crazy
这个秘密麻麻的
The representative lived here for a rather long
代表在这里住了一个相当长的
Then there's a long time here
然后这边还有一个长的时间
Then there are personal ones buried here
然后这边还有个人的有埋葬的这里
Those who saw people die here are buried here
看见人死在这里的就埋在这里
so it's not a temporary
所以它不是一个临时性的来的
it lives here
它就住在这里
So people are buried here when they die
所以人死了就埋在这里
it won't ship back its old furniture
它不会运回它老家具
buried here
埋在这里
The representative here is a jade
这边代表是一个还有玉器
this is a jade
这是一个玉
The representative said that the jade from Taiwan
代表说从台湾来的玉器
they can also bring
他们也可以带来了
Jade
玉器
This is the era we did
这个是我们做的年代
Dated to 3800 at the latest
年代最晚可以到3800年
as early as 4200
最早可以到4200年
this era
这个年代
represents 3800 years
代表3800年
people here at this time
就这个时候的人在这里
Living on Ome Island
在青梅岛上面居住
what they do is make stone tools
他们干什么就是制造石器
I'm going out to see this one
我出去看这一个
Most people can't understand these stones
这些石头一般人看不懂
I can't even read it the first time
连我第一次去看不懂
Later, when I went again, I found
后来再去的时候发现了
There are many mysteries in it
其中有很多奥妙
inside these stones
这些石头里面
I go out to see
我出去看
It's full of scraps from making stone tools.
这里面都是一些制造石器的废料
This scrap it doesn't break down naturally
这个废料它不是自然崩裂的
it is cracked
它是打裂的
So from many traces
所以可以从很多痕迹里面
I can tell
看得出来
most obviously this
最明显是这个
This is called Northwest Bay
这我们叫西北湾
This one is an original manufacture period
这一个是一个当初制造时期
after a long time
经过很长时间
Then it's left on the ground again
然后它就在地面上面又残留下来的
Various scraps of the period when these were made
各种各样的这些打制的时期的废料
so much waste
这些废料那么多
piled up thick
堆得很厚
There is almost no natural stone in it
这里面几乎是没有天然的石头
They are all scraps from the manufacturing period.
都是制造时期的打下来的废料
There are many, many tools from these manufacturing periods in the middle
中间还有很多很多的这些制造时期的工具
The so-called tools are masonry stones
所谓工具就是以石工石
is to hit stone with stone
就是利用石头打石头
so there are some tools
所以有一些工具
As look here there are many
作为看这边有很多
this wonderful one
这个非常精彩的一个
This is probably all over the world
这个大概在全世界
To find such a complete period manufacturing site
要找这么完整的一个时期制造场
almost very hard
几乎是非常难的
we have some in the pacific
我们在太平洋有一些
Mainland China has some
中国大陆有一些
But an immobile like this
但是像这样的一个元风不动的
4,000-year-old
在这里保存了4000年的
Such a site is probably basically
这么一个遗址大概基本上
one is hard to find again
一个很难可以再找得到
Because there is Qimei, no one goes
因为有七美没有人去
also did not destroy
也没有破坏
So here every year through things
所以这边每年经过东西
Spring, summer, autumn and winter go round and round
春夏秋冬就周而复始
It's been like this for four thousand years
这样子经过了四千年
it's always been like this
就一直就是这个样子
so when i look at it
所以当我看它的时候
I feel my heart will be excited
我觉得心头就会激动
I feel that between the ancients
我觉得和古人之间
It's the feeling of meeting
完全是相遇的那种感觉
Can feel the ancients here
可以感受到古人在这里
the way you work
工作的那种样貌
so in my head
所以在我的脑海里面
can emerge
就可以浮现出来
So this was what shocked me at the time.
所以这个是当时也是让我非常震惊的
this discovery
这一个发现
We have also done a lot of analysis during these periods
这些时期我们也做了很多的分析
found inside
发现里面
so many stones inside
那么多的石头里面
In fact, it can be divided into several categories
其实可以分成几大类别
One category is rock that hits fast
一个类别就是会快撞的石料
just a stone
就是一个石材
they from this
他们从这个
after moving above
搬到上面以后
to make a knock down
来做出一个敲下来
become a crashing stone
变成一个快撞的石料
Then generate some stone boxes
然后再产生一些石盒
So the stone box is a mother stone
所以石盒就是一个母石
The above can be further processed
上面可以再进一步的来加工
A call to make stone tools
制造石器的一个call
Then come the flakes
然后过来就是石片
Stone flakes are a basic material for further processing
石片就是说进一步加工的一个基本的素材
Then it becomes a blank and a material
然后变成一个blank 一个素材
Then make a blank in the manufacturing period with the material
然后跟素材里面再做成一个制造时期的一个毛坯
And then there are some stone remnants
然后还有一些是石残器
So remnants are tools
所以残器就是有一些工具
this stone grass it produces a blemish
这石草它产生一个瑕疵
Or it breaks and it's lost
或者破裂之后它就丢掉了
Because there are too many stone residues
因为石残太多了
it doesn't need to stay
它就不需要去留它
it breaks and throws it away
它破了就丢
So often found a very beautiful period
所以往往发现一个很漂亮的时期
But it will be discarded if there is a catastrophe in the middle
但是中间产了一劫它就不要了
Because it is a relatively complete
因为它要运回去是一个比较完整的
It is good
是好的
There are also pebbles
另外还有石子器
What are stone tools?
石子器什么东西呢
It's a tool to beat the times
就是打时期的工具
then this is
那这个是
As a look at this is a so-called stone
作为看这个是所谓一个石材的
a most primitive stone
一个最原始的石材
then slowly beat down
然后慢慢地打下来
turn into small pebbles
变成小碎石片
then come again
然后再过来
this is a flake
这是一个石片
a large square
一个大部分一个方形
or rectangular flakes
或长方形的石片
and then after the challenge
然后再经过挑打之后
These stone flakes
变成快撞的这种石片
Then it slowly took shape
然后慢慢成型了
This is a
这是一个
as a round blank imagining a period
作为想象一个时期的一个圆坯
For example, a rectangle
譬如说长方形
above is where you can shake hands
上面是可以握手的地方
Below is a windblade
下面是一个风刃
It's the wind blade of a utensil
是一个器物的风刃的
this location
這個位置
then it becomes
然後就變成
then slowly take the next step
然後慢慢慢慢的下一步
becomes a
就變成一個
After correction
再經過修正
this fixed
這修正下來
just a small waste
就是產生了一個小的廢料
smaller waste
更小的廢料
and then finally becomes a
然後最後變成一個
a period of formation
一個成型的一個時期
everybody look
各位看
letter
明信
those people are smart
那這些人很聰明
he ends here he ends
他到此他就為止
he didn't do it
他不做了
why not
不做了 為什麼呢
he doesn't need to do it anymore
他不需要再做了
It is enough for him to ship this back to Taiwan
他把這個運回臺灣去就夠了
And then processed after arriving in Taiwan
然後到臺灣之後再加工
So he also had this
所以當時他也有這個
On the one hand, there is the concept of industry collapse
一方面有產業俱落的概念
on the one hand also what
一方面也有什麼
The concept of processing export zones
加工出口區的概念
want to be interesting
很想有意思
when he does
他做的時候
Why
為什麼
He doesn't want to move the whole rock back to Taiwan
他不要把整塊石頭搬回臺灣去
We have to cross the black ditch in the middle
中間要跨過黑水溝
very difficult, right?
很困難的對不對
even in the qing dynasty
即使在清朝的時候
The Han people want to cross the black ditch
漢人要跨過黑水溝
Ten people have seven berths
十個人有七條船位
Ten ships have seven berths silent
十條船有七條船位沉默的
that they
那這個他們
don't have to move the boulder back
不必把大石塊搬回去
After he has increased to this level?
他加到這種程度之後呢
reprocessing in Taiwan
到臺灣再加工
So this is a
所以這個是一個
The system of people at that time, the wisdom of ancient people
當時人的製 古代人的智慧
Then this is the tool of his manufacturing period
那這個是他製造時期的工具
This has been hammered in vain
这个经过圈锤白打
it has been tied
它已经打平了
Do you see it
看到没有
There was a seal and it was flat
本来有封印的打平了
There are so many things like this
这个这种东西非常多
Look at these tools
你看这个这些工具
This manufactures tools at ten kilometres.
这制造以十公时的工具
Then we based on these things
然后我们根据这些东西
we can restore it back then
我们就可以复原它当时人
Steps in each manufacturing period
每个制造时期的步骤
can restore it
可以把它复原起来
one recovered
一个复原起来
Then this is the person we imagined at the time
然后这个是我们想象的当时人
how to make period
怎么去制造时期的
This step draws it
这个步骤把它画过
see this as
这个作为看
This is the whole Ome Island
这个是整个青梅岛
above this
上面这个
This is where the drama of it falls
这是它的剧落在这里
Humans sleep here at night
人类晚上在这里睡觉的
sleep
睡觉
he goes out during the day
他白天就出去
Go to this location where there is this injection of Xuanwu Garden
到这个有这个注装宣武园的这个位置上面
then what
然后就就什么呢
just step on the stone and hit
就去踩石头就打
Watching the sea and singing folk songs every day
每天看海唱山歌在里面
then this
然后这样
then stop after
然后打住后
Just after forming a batch
刚刚形成了一个出批之后
then here
然后就这边
It just so happens that this is a bay
刚好这是个海湾
bay
海湾
Then it's out to sea
然后这边就出海了
Then it can be shipped elsewhere
然后就可以运到别的地方去了
Where does this luck go?
那这个那这个运哪里去呢
This is one of Japan's era scholars Kokubu
这是日本时代学者国分之一
he also studies
他也研究
He found that in southwestern Taiwan
他发现在台湾西南部的
From south of Taichung
从台中以南
Probably to the generation of Pingtung
大概到屏东这一代
Many wills are unearthed inside the period
很多意志里面都出土的时期
Xuan Wuyan
都是宣武炎
That's where Xuan Wuyan came from
那是宣武炎从哪里来的
He presumed it was from Penghu
他推设是来自于澎湖的
So he was the first to bring up
所以他最早提出来
So Xuanwuyan in southern Taiwan
所以台湾南部的宣武炎
is a scholar from Penghu
是来自于澎湖的学者
Now our findings can be further confirmed by
现在我们的发现可以进一步的证实了
Watch carefully
注意看
This is the period of Xuanwuyan in southern Taiwan
这是台湾南部地区的宣武炎的时期
is very beautiful
是很漂亮的
right
对不对
The model is very delicate
模特非常精致
This is not available in Penghu
这个在澎湖是没有的
right
对不对
Penghu means
澎湖就是说
After he punched out the fur of the thing
他把东西一个毛皮打出来之后
Shipped to Taiwan
运了台湾
and then process
然后再加工
then spread out
然后再分散出去
So the rep said
所以代表说
The earliest processing export zone
最早的加工出口区
this
这个
I didn't know if I slept
当初不知道有没有睡
do not know
不晓得
then this is
那这个是
Watch carefully
注意看
The period of this stone in Taiwan
这个石头在台湾的时期
are very delicate
都非常的精致
So our hypothesis
所以我们这个推设
Penghu Century Factory
澎湖这个世纪制造厂
It is not just the meaning of manufacturing technology
它本身不只是制造技术上的意义
it was at the time
它在当时
ancient human trade
古代的人類貿易
The circulation of the goods
這個貨物的流通方面
In fact, it also has a very important meaning in it.
其實也具有很重要的意義在裡面
Then this part of its circulation
那麼這個它流通的部分
On the one hand to Taiwan
一方面到台灣
it is mostly southern taiwan
它主要是台灣南部
It is almost not found in northern Taiwan
在台灣北部幾乎是沒有發現
from Taichung
就從台中大概
South of Zuoshuixi
左水溪以南
It has probably been this generation until Pingtung
一直到屏東這一代大概都是它
Another scholar's
另外這個學者的
Research by foreign scholars
國外學者研究
On Dongshan Island in Fujian
在福建的東山島上面
some periods unearthed inside the chair
椅子裡面出土的一些時期
After some isotopic analysis
經過一些同位素的分析
Analysis of trace elements
經過微量元素的分析
It was also found that these things all came from Penghu Island
也發現這些東西都是來自於澎湖島
So this thing becomes very interesting
所以這個東西就變得非常有意思
Therefore, the period of Qimei Island in Penghu
所以澎湖的這個七美島的時期
It is not only to Taiwan
它不只到台灣
It also went to Fujian
它也到福建去了
So this represents five thousand years in ancient times
所以這個代表在古代五千年
four to five thousand years ago
四五千年以前
Here is a very important
這邊是具有一個非常重要的
one place with one meaning
一個意義的一個地方
many people ask me
很多人問我
He said what ship he was on
他說當時人在什麼船
It is not so easy to cross the black ditch
跨過黑水溝不是那麼容易的
I said I'm sorry I don't know
我說對不起我也不知道
we didn't find
我們沒有發現
We can only speculate that probably
我們只能推測大概是這樣子
Because motor boats were impossible at the time
因為當時不可能有機動船
may be troublesome
可能靠得风烦
to take advantage of the good weather
来利用天气好的时候
to cross the trench
来跨越到海水沟
but sea trench
但是海水沟
Although it is about sea trenches
虽然是讲海水沟
It's actually very difficult
其实是非常的困难
Our School Archeology Team
我们的学校考古队伍
Experience crossing the sea trench several times
好几次经验跨过海水沟
it is very difficult
的确是非常困难
very thrilling
非常惊险
So four or five thousand years ago in ancient times
所以古代的四五千年以前
how do humans carry so many stones
人类如何带着这么多石头
How to cross the sea trench
怎么去跨越海水沟
From Penghu to Taiwan
从澎湖到台湾
From Penghu to Fujian
从澎湖到福建去
This is a big puzzle
这个都是一个很大的一个谜题
we all need
我们都需要
On the one hand we are wary
一方面我们很战探
the wisdom of the ancients
古代人的智慧
On the one hand we are also very
一方面我们也非常的
how to solve this puzzle
这个谜题怎么去了解
ancient humans
古代的人类
Here is a model we built
这是我们建立的一个模型
these are the ingredients
就是这些食材
between the whole area
在整个区域之间
in trade
在贸易上 交易上的
A model generated
所产生的一个model
this is ours
这是我们的
relationship of our time
我们时间的关系
i want the fastest
我想最快很快的
tell me again
再讲一下
then another
那么另外一个
Sea Wonders
海域奇葩
we know taiwan
我们知道台湾
You are studying and don't know
诸位在学不知道
Taiwan is in the whole of East Asia
台湾是在整个东亚地区
One of the centers of a very important anticipation
一个很重要的预期的中心之一
As long as China is a big country
只要中国大国
There are several important prospective centers on the mainland
在大陸有幾個重要的預期中心
Hongshan Culture in the Northeast
在東北的紅山文化
Two Groups of Cultures in the South
在南方的兩組文化
in Hangzhou, Zhejiang
在浙江杭州一帶
Then the Gansu area in the west
然後西邊的甘肅一帶
are the centers of several important expectations
都是幾個重要的預期的中心
Taiwan is one of them
我們台灣是其中之一
is also an important center of anticipation
也是一個重要的預期中心
why
為什麼呢
Because there is a bathroom in Taiwan
因為台灣有一個浴況
Fengtian Field in East Hualien
在東部花蓮的風田域
it is a domain
它是一個產域的
thus creating Taiwan
因此造就了台灣
for thousands of years
在好幾千年以來
is a very important anticipation center
就是一個很重要的預期的中心
About five thousand years ago
大概目前發現到五千年
Humans have already started using anticipation
人類已經開始使用預期了
current expectations
目前這個預期
In all the ruins in Taiwan
在台灣所有的遺址裡面
Both found the expected
都發現了預期
inclusive from north to south
包含從北到南
From Main Island to Outer Islands
從本島到外島
almost all expected
幾乎都有預期
Just like Green Island and Orchid Island, both have been found and expected
就像綠島 蘭嶼都有發現到預期
I remember two years ago
我記得兩年以前
I went to Green Island to see a ruin
我到綠島去看一個遺址
the surface of the ruins
那遺址表面
you can't see anything
你看不到什麼東西了
I see a friend go
我看一個朋友去
a foreign scholar
一個外國學者
His purpose is to find expectations
他的目的就是要找預期
Looking for a long time is very disappointed
要找的半天很失望
We don't see
我們看本來沒有
As a result, when I want to turn back later
結果後來我要回頭的時候
I kicked
我一腳一踢
just kick out a bath gas
就踢出一件浴氣出來
so he is envious
所以他很羨慕
he has medicine
他有藥
i said no
我說不可以
This is the heritage of our country's culture
這是我們的國家的文化之產
you can't take it
你不可以拿走
this
這個
We know that the current bath gas in Taiwan
我們知道現在台灣的浴氣
very widely distributed
分布得非常的廣
this
這個
I think the relationship of this time
我想這個時間的關係
Most of them are in Taitung
其中最多的是台東的
transplant
移植
it unearthed bath gas
它出土的浴氣
Much
非常多
Now there are more than five or six thousand pieces
現在目前有五六千件以上的
unearthed from the same transplant
同一個移植所出土的
the bath gas itself
這些浴氣本身
can be divided into several categories
可以分成好幾個類別
One is the so-called decorator class
一個是所謂的裝飾類
Light Drama
光劇類
Weapons
武器類
You can look at these pictures
各位可以看看這些圖片
very beautiful
非常的漂亮
The technology of our Taiwan bath gas
我們台灣浴氣的工藝技術
Actually it's not bad at all
其實真的一點都不差
not bad at all
一點都不差
So I speak Haiyu Qipan
所以我講的海語奇盤
In Taiwan's Haiyu Barren State
在台灣的海語荒州的
inside this corner
這個角落裡面
there are still
竟然還有
there is such a beautiful
存在著這麼精美的
craft of healing
治癒的工藝
everybody look
各位看
The bath gas is very beautiful
浴氣非常的精美
very beautiful
非常精美
The bath quality is also very beautiful
浴質也非常漂亮
everybody look
各位看
these are earrings earrings
這些這是耳環耳飾
look
你看
Different kinds
各種各樣的
These II, you see
这些二世 诸位看
Compared with the jade aura of the mainland, this is actually true
这这个比起大陆的玉气其实真的
It really doesn't matter in terms of craftsmanship, craftsmanship, or shape
真的不管从造工 造工艺上面 造型方面
Actually not bad
其实都不差
Look at this is very beautiful jade gas
你看这个是非常漂亮的玉气
This and this very famous
这个还有这个非常有名的
The so-called life type has a birthday
所谓人寿型 上面点了一个寿
such two people
这么两个人
This Taiwan has now discovered that there are two or three worlds
这个台湾现在目前发现了有二三世间的
Such a kind of jade appears
这样的一种玉气出现
very beautiful
非常漂亮
This is Taitung Stone Statue Red Museum
这是台东石像红博物馆
You take this as its authority
你把这个作为它的管威
You guys look very beautiful too
诸位看也是非常的漂亮的
Then this is another site outside the North and South
然后这个是在北南之外的别的遗址
Also found the same kind of jade gas
也发现同样的这类的玉气
Look at these gems
诸位看这些玉气
So Taiwan's jade gas is very exquisite
所以台湾的玉气是非常的精美的
it has such an important
它有这么一个重要
Ten thousand generations of ancient humans in Taiwan
十千世代台湾古代的人类
In fact, there is such a very important tradition of jade
其实有这么一个很重要的玉气的一个传统
Then this is this is a jade tube
那这个是这是一个玉管
That's a puzzle too
那这个也是一个谜题
It can be up to 30 cm in length
这个大概长度也可以到30公分
Such a long, very narrow, small round tube
这么长的一个非常很窄的一个小圆管
available from this
可以从这个
can penetrate to the other side
可以穿透到另外一邊
so you use water
所以你用水
This side can be used as a water pipe
從這邊可以當水管
can flow to the other side
可以流到另外一邊去
so this is a puzzle
所以這個是一個謎題
how did you do it
到底怎麼做出來的
ten generations before
在十前十代
Well this is on top of the world
那麼這個在世界上面
It's hard to have such expectations
就背難有這種預期
such a long tube
那麼長的預管
this is very delicate
這個非常的精緻
And the middle will not be broken
而且中間不會被破掉
And penetrate
而且貫通
This craft is very rare
這個工藝非常難得的
This section has been a few months ago
這個部分已經在幾個月以前
Implemented as national security by the Ministry of Culture
被文化部執行為國保
This is the expectation of the national security level
這是國保級的這個預期
this is very beautiful these
這個是非常漂亮的這些
This pre-value is very good pre-value
這個預值非常好的預值
you want to do this
你要這個做一看
I want everyone to take a look
我想大家一看一看
Then this expected mineral source
那麼這個預期的這個礦源
The only source of minerals in Taiwan is here
台灣唯一的礦源就在這裡
In the so-called Toyota domain
在所謂豐田域
Well, recently our colleagues are here
那麼最近我們的同仁在這邊
also do research
也做調查
Several new ruins were discovered
又發現了幾個好幾個新的遺址
near here
就在這附近
Anyway, here is a mining area near here
反正這邊是一個礦區在這附近
So a lot of the anticipation is coming from this area
所以大量的預期都是來自於這個地區
what is expected of its production
那這個預期它的生產的預期
not just to north and south
不只是到北南
North-South is a consumer
北南是一個消費
Then he actually changed his steps to Taiwan from high to low
那他這個其實換步到台灣的從高到低
From the main island to the outer islands, the whole island is
從本島到外島 全島都是
So on behalf of a trade network about expectations at that time
所以代表當時一個關於預期的一個貿易網
It's a big trade network
就是很大的貿易網
Thousands of years ago, these beautiful expectations of human beings
在幾千年以前人類這些這個漂亮的預期
circulates throughout this
就流通在整個的這個
But apart from Taiwan
但是除了台灣本之外呢
In fact, more importantly
其實更重要的是
This is this, this, this, this, this, this, roe
這就是這個這個風田域的這個這個魚子
This wind is called Hirabayashi roe
這個風叫平林魚子
i want to take a look
我想看一看
This one has a lot of manufacturing expectations on top of the roe
這個在魚子上面有很多的製造預期
leftover scrap
剩下的廢料
You see he was making an expectation
你看他當時他要做一個預期
he wants to be round
他要做圓的
He can't be cut with wire now
他不是現在可以用線切割
He cut it piece by piece like this
他用一塊一塊一塊一塊這樣切下來
look over there
你看看那邊
After the corners are cut slowly
先角落慢慢切圓以後
Then grind it into a round
然後再磨變成圓的
It's a waste of work
其實很廢工的
But he made so many expectations
但是他做那麼多預期
It means that apart from the tools at that time
代表當時的這個除了工具之外呢
Maybe there was a lot of manpower at that time, and he looked like this
可能當時的人力也不少的他這樣子
So so create these expectations
那麼所以製造這些預期
Well, this is how to make
那麼這個是製造的方法
Our scholars have done a lot of research in this area
我們學者做很多的這方面研究
how to make these expectations
怎麼去做這些預期
how to use
怎么去使用
Then the other is the expectation
那么另外一个就是这个预期
Not only in Taiwan
不止在台湾
one of my students
我的一个学生
he did research
他做了研究
He expected Taiwan
他把台湾预期
do some component analysis
做一些成分的分析
him and the philippines
他和菲律宾
and Thailand
和泰国
and analysis done elsewhere
和其他地方做的分析
Found in Vietnam and Thailand
发现在越南和泰国
Thailand's Indochina Peninsula
泰国的中南半岛
Southside has some expectations
南边的有一些预期
Almost from Taiwan
几乎就是来自于台湾
Feng Tian from Taiwan
来自于台湾的封田
Then the scientist
然后这个科学家
our geoscience institute
我们的地球科学所的
Dr. Zong Fan
范总博士
He also helped out with some testing.
他也帮忙来做一些检测
found that it looks from the ingredients
发现从成分上面看起来
From the characteristics it seems
从特征上看起来
In fact, in many places in Southeast Asia
其实在东南亚很多地方
Expected to be from Taiwan
预期是来自于台湾
Therefore, on behalf of Taiwan, these expectations at that time
所以代表台湾当时这些预期
It is not only circulated in the islands of Taiwan
它不只是流通在全台湾各岛
Main Island Outer Island
本岛外岛
also spread out
同时也向外去扩散
like arriving in the philippines
像到达菲律宾
Arrive in South Vietnam
到达越南南部
Also to the south of Thailand
也是到达泰国南部
So the range is very wide
所以这个范围非常的广
this thing
这个东西
can make us go very wow
可以让我们去很赞叹
The wisdom and abilities of the ancients
古代人的智慧和能力
this is
这个是
did these scientific analyzes
做了这些科学的分析
To show what is expected of Taiwan and surrounding areas
來顯示出來臺灣預期和周邊地區
Expected Relationships in Other Regions
其他地區預期的關係
This is what the entire expectation finds
這個是整個的預期所發現的
such a zone
這樣的一個區帶
Because Taiwan has always been very popular
臺灣因為向來蠻流傳
we can forget about it
可以大家把它忘掉
so
這樣
Well, my relationship at this time
好了我現在這個時間的關係
I'm probably past the time
我大概已經超過了時間了
So so our archeology
那麼所以我們這個考古學
Research on ancient humans in Taiwan
對於臺灣古代人類的研究
In fact, through archaeological research
其實透過考古學的研究
In fact, it broadens our horizons for Taiwanese
其實擴大了我們對於臺灣人的視野
we are not living at home
我們不是居家居居
Our current Taiwanese
我們現在目前的臺灣人
Taiwanese have tens of thousands of years of history
臺灣人有幾萬年的歷史
continue history
繼續歷史
then this help
那麼這個幫助
Now we can take people from Taiwan
現在我們可以把臺灣的人
It can also be from 30,000 years to 400 years
也可以從三萬年一直到四百年
can be divided into many different paragraphs
可以分成很多不同的段落
people of different ages
有不同時代的人
then this is a chronology
那這個是一個年表
This is my personal build
這是我個人建立
as can be seen
作為可以看到
The earlier the more simple
越早的時候越單純
it's getting late
到了越晚的時候
The more culturally differentiated
文化分化的越多
in different regions for different cultures
在不同地區對於不同的文化
Representing cultural diversity
代表文化的多元化
this so from these things
這個所以從這些東西裡面
We can find a common
我們可以發現到一個共同的
similarity locus
一些類似性軌跡
The first one is Takuko outside Atom Island
第一個是原子島外的拓子
All cultures from ancient times to the present
所有的文化從古到今
It has been from outside the island since 30,000 years ago
從三萬年以來都是從島外來的
Came here from Southeast Asia
從東南大陸東南亞這樣過來的
The second is the expansion of the interior of the coast
第二個是海岸內陸的擴張
are slowly expanding from the coast to the inland
都是從海岸慢慢向內陸去擴張
like early prehistoric times
像不管是早期的史前時代
or Han Chinese
或者漢人
That is, from the coast to the inland slowly
也就是從海岸慢慢向內陸去
expand slowly
慢慢擴張
another third
另外第三個
Diversification of Taiwan's terrain and environment
台灣的地形的環境的多樣化
Therefore, a lot of local environment-adapted
所以產生了很多適應地方環境的
these cultures
這些文化
The appearance of different cultures
不同的文化的樣貌
So represent a very full kind of
所以代表一種很充分的一種
Variety of Ecological Adaptations
生態適應的多樣化
diversity
多樣性
The fourth is the island of Taiwan
第四個是台灣海島
So since ancient times
所以自古至今
Coastal trade is an important
海岸貿易是一個很重要的
you see from thousands of years ago
你看從幾千年前
Anticipated Hanwai Interactive Transactions
預期的漢外的互動交易
Until the era of popular sentiment
一直到了民情時代的
Trade between Taiwan's aborigines and Han Chinese
台灣的原住民和漢人之間的交易
It was Penghu and the main island four or five thousand years ago
是四五千年前的澎湖和本島
In fact, this maritime transaction has always been a very constant behavior pattern
其實這海上交易一直是一個非常不斷的行為模式
sorry
對不起
Finally, we give some enlightenment to the Taiwanese
最後我們給台灣人給我們一些啟示
What kind of enlightenment do we get from these studies?
我們從這些研究裡面到底有什麼樣的啟示
The first one is the favorite small island marine military area
第一個是最愛的小島海洋軍區
Taiwan is a small island, but in all directions
台灣這個小島但是四面八方
These people can come to Taiwan from all directions
這些人可以從四面八方來到台灣
keep coming in waves
不斷一波一波的來
first come first serve
先來後到多元會催
The third is the continuous development of the sea railway
第三個是滄海上鐵綿延發展
Taiwan's topography and landforms are constantly changing
台灣地形地貌隨著不斷的改變
But human beings have nothing to do with adapting to the environment
但是人類它與適應環境
It can continue to develop from nearly ten thousand years to the present
它能夠繼續的從近萬年以來一直發展到今
Then Bilu men and women actually have success
然後必路男女竟然有成
It's all worked out
都是經過打拚出來的
look at ancient life
你看古代的生活
It has to adapt to the environment
它都要去適應這個環境
Utilize the best strategies
利用各種最好的策略
and get the best life
而獲取最好的生活
and until now
然後一直到至於今
so finally
所以最後
I have some thoughts
我一点感想
In fact, we feel that what we just saw on the first page
其实我们觉得现在刚刚前面第一页看到的
Many people are arguing about who is Taiwanese.
很多人为了这些谁是台湾人在里面争
Looking at it online, I think some are ridiculous
作为上网路看一看觉得有的很可笑
really ridiculous
真的很可笑
there is bullshit
有胡扯
or some are simply stubborn
或者有些根本在硬拗
or how
或者怎么样
In fact, I think we don't need to spend time fighting over who is Taiwanese.
其实我觉得我们不必在花时间去斗谁是台湾人
In fact, from these ancient people
其实从这古代人的这些
experienced history looks
经历的历史看起来
The people who live and work hard on this land are Taiwanese
这个土地上安生立命努力打平的人就是台湾人
these ancient ancients
这些古代古代人
You can see that they slowly reproduce his descendants in this land bit by bit
你看他们一点一滴的在这个土地上慢慢的翻演他的后代
then until now
然后一直到现在为止
where especially in today's global competition
那里特别是在今天这个全球竞争
Era of not advancing or retreating
不进择退的时代
Should we Taiwanese not be able to disagree?
我们台湾人应该要不能够不分歧吗
Our Taiwan now looks more and more regressive
我们的台湾现在看起来是越来越退步
Well, this is a very boring psychology.
那这个是一个非常让人家很闷的一个心理
Recently our Ma Ying-jeou is also bored
最近我们马英九也很闷
it's definitely boring
就绝对是很闷
Because Taiwan is not progressing
因为台湾不进步
Make everyone the most bored
再让大家最闷了
So I hope everyone will come together to disagree
所以希望大家一起来分歧
OK
好不好
thank you all
谢谢大家
Thanks
谢谢
There are only five minutes left for Mr. Zhang's wonderful service and protection.
張先生這個非常精彩服務與保護能只剩五分鐘
But we allow three problems
但是我們容許三個問題
First
第一個
there is a third
還有第三個
that's all
就這樣
Thank you, teacher
謝謝老師
Super wonderful speech
超精彩演講
Do not know at all
都不知道
Archaeological lectures will be so passionate
考古的演講會這麼熱血
and so funny
而且這麼有趣
what i want to ask is
我想請教的是
One of the places I'm most interested in is
我最感興趣的一個地方就是
Questions about the first dog in Taiwan
關於台灣第一狗的問題
The teacher just mentioned that
老師剛剛有提到說
The first dog in Taiwan was buried well
台灣第一狗他好好的被暗葬
say with common imagination
跟一般想像說
Dogs may die in some villages
狗可能在某些村落死掉
Just throw it away, it doesn't seem to be the same
就丟掉好像不太一樣
But you just mentioned that
但是你們剛剛有提到說
These people should be from South China
這些人他們應該是來自華南
They are also used to coming from South China
來自華南他們也習慣
Want to keep their original village habits
想要保持他們原來的村落習慣
Because after all the environment is also similar
因為畢竟環境也相似
But if they are in their hometown
可是如果他們在原鄉
The general imagination is to throw the dog away
一般的想像是會把狗亂丟
Then why do you love dogs so much when you come to Taiwan?
那怎麼到了台灣就這麼愛狗
mean the dog they brought
是說他們帶來的狗
So the feeling is very good
所以感情特別好
or in the hometown
還是說在原鄉
the dog they brought
他們帶來的狗
So the feeling is very good
所以感情特別好
Or the dog in Taiwan
還是說在台灣的狗
The special reason they feel getting along
他們覺得相處的特別原因
Or, does the teacher have some explanations for this place?
或是 就是說老師對這一個地方有沒有一些解釋
That is to say, he seems to be
就是說他跟原來的習慣似乎
Or the part that seems to be different from the original imagination
或是原來的想像好像不太一樣的部分
Thanks
謝謝
Because I don't know how they are in the opposite corner of South China
因為我不知道華南他們對角怎麼樣
Maybe it's fun too Maybe
說不定也很愉快 說不定
do not know
不曉得
Then this is indeed what we can see from our archaeological phenomena
那這個的確是我們從我們的考古現象看起來
it is so
的確是如此這樣子
This is a dog, look at this, it deliberately buries its smoke
這一個狗 你看這個把它刻意的煙埋起來
And then let it go to sleep
然後還讓它變成一個睡覺的狀態
It's not good to throw it away
不是一丟就好了
I take good care of the door
我好好的安門
between human and dog
代表人和人 狗之間的
I think the whole society at that time
我想那個時候整個社會形態
Dogs are very important to their upbringing
狗對他們養育是非常重要
He was hunted and mutilated
他受獵 分屍一些
Probably
大概是
But Nianwei must be the number one dog in Taiwan
但是A年衛這一定是台灣第一狗
so far
現在目前為止
Doctor Zhang, please
張醫師 請問一下
That year when you mentioned that it was the Changbing culture
那年你剛剛提到說是長兵文化的時候
It is now found to be almost 30,000 years ago
現在發現是差不多三萬年前
After that, there was another fault for a while
那接著的時候有一段時間的時候又有一個斷層
Then why is there a fault
那為什麼會有一個斷層
Are the two faults the same?
那這個斷層兩個是不是說是同一個
democracy
民主
The next time is according to the present time
接著的時候是根據現在的時候
We are now Taiwan's aboriginal Gao Shanzhu
我們現在台灣的原住民高山主
Or it doesn't seem to have anything to do with those
或者什麼又跟那一些好像都沒有關係
why is this
為什麼會有這樣
We are still studying this issue
這個問題我們目前還在研究
I am now a preliminary
我現在一個初步的
I had a speech a while ago and I also mentioned
我前陣子有一個演講我也提到了
This gap is obvious
這個斷層很明顯
From about 15,000 onwards
大概從15000年以後
The next session will be about 6000, 5000 years
下屆就大概6000、5000年
There is a GAP in the middle like this
這樣中間有一個GAP這樣子
Then this GAP
那麼這個GAP的話
it's on culture
它就在文化上面
It has basically not entered the new era
它基本上還沒有進入到新時期時代
So its period is still typed
所以它的時期還是打字的
hardly naughty
幾乎沒有淘氣
not like this
沒有這樣子
but it has some differences
但是它有一些差別
it has many tricks
它的實騙器很多
so fake
所以實騙器
This real cheat is playing
這個實騙器就是打起來
Use real deception instead of verification
利用實騙而不是利用實核
in this way
這樣子
I'm making a preliminary guess about this
這個東西我現在一個初步推測
The same culture is actually more than just long soldiers
同樣的文化其實不只長兵
It was also found once in several places in southern Taiwan
在台灣南部好幾個地方也發現了一次
my bold guess
我一個大膽的推測
This is similar to that of many tribes in Taiwan in the past
這個是和台灣過去很多部落裡面的
a legend little black person like relationship
一個傳說小黑人之類的關係
Well, this thing is very similar to the Philippines
那麼這個東西和菲律賓倒是非常類似
Now five or six thousand years ago there were still little black people
现在在五六千年以前还有小黑人存在
Taiwan is in many tribes
台湾在很多部落里面
There are also legends about little black people in the aboriginal tribes
原住民部落里面还有小黑人的传说
In the end it was obviously Saisiyat
最后明明是赛夏族的
It doesn't matter between these little black men
这些汉小黑人之间也没关系
I think it's worth thinking about
我想可以值得我去思考
So recently I was also discussing such a question
所以最近我也在讨论这样一个问题
Because the aborigines in Taiwan are pushing up
因为台湾目前原住民往上推
Pushing it to 2000 will not make it up
推到2000年就推不上去了
But in many tribal legends
但是很多部落传说里面
There are many, many legends with little black people
有很多很多都有小黑人的传说
dwarf legend
矮人传说
The legend but now the dwarves are gone
这个传说但是现在矮人都消失不见了
Is it possible that this thing is such a group of people?
这东西有没有可能是那么一批人
from the Philippines
来自于菲律宾的
This part I'm here for a bold
这个部分我这是为一个大胆的
currently it is a guess
目前它是一个推测
Maybe we need to go further and do some discussions
也许还要进步的去做一些讨论
But between the CAP of the Chinese Academy of Sciences and the longevity culture
但是这中院的CAP和长命文化之间
It should have nothing to do with the ethnic group.
应该是在族群上面也是没有关系的
in this way
这样子
Okay, thank you
好 谢谢
There is also a problem
这也还有一个问题
consult
请教
Ask Professor Zhang
请教张教授
Just saw that in the picture
刚在图片里面有看到那个
That front tooth is missing
那門牙缺了一顆
The professor said it was
那教授有說那就是
Aboriginal people have this tooth extraction custom
原住民有這種拔牙習俗
then ask the professor
那麼請教教授
How can there be such a tooth extraction
怎麼會有這種拔牙齒拔掉
What does it mean
這是什麼意思
right this this
對 這個 這個
like what is a needle
像針是什麼
yes this is actually
對 這個其實
in time era
在時間時代
this tooth extraction practice
這個拔牙習俗
eastward across the continent
在整個大陸東聯海
down from Shandong
從山東一直下來
This is available in Taiwan
到台灣都有這個
Many can be found with the practice of tooth extraction
很多可以發現有拔牙的習俗
aborigines until now
到現在原住民
like the strugglers
像一直到拼搏族
there will be many more
都會有很多還有
until now no more
到現在沒有了
at least until the sun rises
至少在日日上以前
There is also the custom of tooth extraction
都還有拔牙的習俗
Then this is in a biological theory
那這個是在一種生命理理
Well like some of you grown up
那麼像有一些你成年了
He is going to use the adult theory
他就要去用成年理
in this way
這樣子
Some are in a special
有一些是在一種特殊的
under this requirement
這個要求之下
like military exploits
像有戰功
Or the girl is an adult
或者女孩子這個成年了
he will also pull teeth
他也會拔牙
Then we are within the will of Taiwan
那我們在台灣的這個意志裡面
also found
也發現
In some tribes, all boys have their teeth pulled
有的部落里面是完全男生拔牙
But in some tribes, both boys and girls pull their teeth
但有的部落里面是男生女生都拔牙
So it represents the customs and habits of each tribe
所以代表着每一个部落的风俗习惯
basically different
基本上是不一样的
Of course tooth extraction will hurt
当然拔牙会痛
no pain
痛也没办法
its habit like we used to
它的习惯就像我们过去
This woman like the Chinese wants to have small feet
像中国人的这个女的要过小脚
It hurts to have too small feet
过小脚是很痛的
right
对不对
she never had small feet
她不从来过小脚
she became a custom
她就变成一个风俗了
everybody do this
大家每个人都要这么做
You feel a shame if you don't pull your teeth
你不拔牙就觉得是一个羞耻
don't pull your feet
不去拔小脚
that's a shame
那是一个羞耻那样子
So this becomes a
所以这变成一个
a customary habit
约定俗成的一个习惯
a ceremony
一种仪式
so she has to follow
所以她必须要去遵循
a constraint of such a culture
这样一个文化的一种制约
in this way
这样子
this is incredible
这个很不可思议
Thanks
谢谢
it's raining today
今天这个下雨天
Thank you very much for being so active
各位这么踴躍非常感谢
Archeology is hard work
考古是一门很辛苦的工作
and requires cross-disciplinary knowledge
而且需要跨领域的知识
In fact, a lot of natural science knowledge is needed
其实还要很多自然科学知识
and really hard
而且真的很辛苦
It's hard to get a little knowledge
要得到一点知识很辛苦
I remember that Mr. Zhang wanted to
我记得张先生那时候要
Ask me to see the Eight Immortals Cave Ruins
要我去看八仙洞遗址
I see so high
我一看那么高
I'm going to do it for so long and dare not say
我要去搞这么久不敢说
But they are walking on flat ground
可是他們那邊像走平地一樣
The quantitative guide that Mr. Chen Zhongyi talked about last time is also
上次陳仲義先生講的那個量導的也是
The first two graduates who are both very tall
都很高的這個前兩位教畢
so it's really not easy
所以真的是很不容易
organize an archeology
組織一個考古
The test pile with Master Jing is like Master Jing's army
對跟菁爺的考堆像菁爺一支軍隊一樣
It's really like Jing Ye's army
真的像菁爺一支軍隊一樣
There are many different kinds of people
人員是多 各式各樣的
Like those post-production studies on the Nanke site
好像南科遺址的那些後製的研究
It's all in that railway warehouse.
都是在那個鐵路的倉庫裡面
Various charts in the large warehouse
大片倉庫裡面各種圖表
just wow like forming an army
就是哇 像組織一支軍隊
Be prepared to be romantic like a lamp stove
要準備浪漫地燈爐一樣
So this is very complicated and very hard
所以這個很複雜 很辛苦
It is not easy to gain some knowledge
得一些知識很不容易
We thank Academician Zhang for his wonderful speech today
我們今天謝謝張院士精采的演講
Thanks
謝謝